<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Fax fonte accensa, fire out of water: or, An endeavour to kindle devotion, from the consideration of the fountains God hath made Designed for the benefit of those who use the waters of Tunbridg-Wells, the Bath, Epsom, Scarborough, Chigwell, Astrop, Northall, &amp;c. Two sermons preached at New Chappel by Tunbridg-Wells. With devout meditations of Cardinal Bellarmin upon fountains of waters. Also some form of meditations, prayers, and thanksgivings, suited to the occasion. By Anthony Walker, D.D.</title>
            <author>Walker, Anthony, d. 1692.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 175 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 103 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96681</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W302A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230546</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899499</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899499</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153725</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96681)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153725)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2375:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Fax fonte accensa, fire out of water: or, An endeavour to kindle devotion, from the consideration of the fountains God hath made Designed for the benefit of those who use the waters of Tunbridg-Wells, the Bath, Epsom, Scarborough, Chigwell, Astrop, Northall, &amp;c. Two sermons preached at New Chappel by Tunbridg-Wells. With devout meditations of Cardinal Bellarmin upon fountains of waters. Also some form of meditations, prayers, and thanksgivings, suited to the occasion. By Anthony Walker, D.D.</title>
                  <author>Walker, Anthony, d. 1692.</author>
                  <author>Bellarmino, Roberto Francesco Romolo, Saint, 1542-1621. Selections, English, 1684.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 166, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Nathaniel Ranew at the King's-Arms in St. Paul's Church-Yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXXV. [1685]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisements bound at beginning and end of text.</note>
                  <note>A reissue of the 1684 edition (Wing W302).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, D.C..</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mineral waters --  Therapeutic use --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Baths --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Meditations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:153725:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153725:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153725:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153725:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153725:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153725:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153725:4"/>
            <head>The ſame Author hath alſo publiſhed,</head>
            <p>THE <hi>Vertuous Woman found,</hi> her Loſs bewail'd, and Character exemplified. In a Sermon preached at the Funeral of that moſt Exellent and Religious Lady, the Right Honourable <hi>MARY</hi> Counteſs Dowager of <hi>VVARVVICK,</hi> the moſt Illuſtrious Patern of ſincere Piety and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid Goodneſs this Age hath produced; to which is annexed ſome of her Ladiſhip's pious and uſeful Meditations.</p>
            <p>The great Evil of Procraſtination; or the Sinfulneſs and Danger of deferring Repentance. In ſeveral Diſcourſes.</p>
            <p>A Sermon preached before the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of <hi>Apothecaries</hi> on <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10.1. publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the Requeſt of the ſaid Company.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Say on:</hi> Or, a ſeaſonable Plea for a full hearing betwixt Man and Man; and a ſerious Plea for the like hearing betwixt God and Man: in a Sermon preached at the Aſſizes at <hi>Chelmsford</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All four ſold by <hi>Nathaniel Ranew,</hi> at the King's-Arms in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153725:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Fax Fonte Accenſa,</hi> Fire out of Water: OR, An Endeavour to kindle Devotion, from the Conſideration of the FOUNTAINS God hath made.</p>
            <p>Deſigned for the Benefit of thoſe who uſe the Waters of TUNBRIDG<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>WELLS, the <hi rend="blackletterType">Bath, Epſom, Scarborough, Chigwell, Aſtrop, Northall,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Two SERMONS preached at New Chappel by <hi rend="blackletterType">Tunbridg-Wells.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With Devout Meditations of Cardinal <hi>Bellarmin</hi> upon Fountains of Waters.</p>
            <p>Alſo ſome Forms of Meditations, Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and Thanksgivings, ſuited to the occaſion.</p>
            <p>By ANTHONY WALKER, D.D.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>O ye Wells, bleſs ye the Lord, praiſe him, and magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy him for ever.</hi> 
               <bibl>Song of the three Children.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Nathaniel Ranew</hi> at the King's-Arms in St. <hi>Paul'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Church-Yard. MDCLXXXV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:153725:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153725:5"/>
            <head>THE Epiſtle Dedicatory TO <hi>Mr.</hi> NATHANIEL HAWS, Citizen of <hi>London,</hi> and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer of <hi>Chriſt-Church Hoſpital.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Friend;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HO the mutual In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercourſe of kind and good Offices, which hath ſome Years paſt betwixt us, and eſpecially at <hi>Tunbridg</hi>-Wells, might excuſe, yea oblige me to ſo open an Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Senſe I have of
<pb facs="tcp:153725:6"/> your Civilities and Friendſhip, and the inſcribing your Name upon theſe Papers without fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proſpect of you, than in your ſingle and perſonal Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, would be too ſmall a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn for thoſe Kindneſſes, by which I am become your Deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor.</p>
            <p>Yet give me leave to tell you, I herein conſider you under that more publick Character, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with your Zeal, your Coſt, your Pains about the erecting of that commodious, beautiful and Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant Structure of the Chappel, we all here injoy the benefit of, juſtly inveſts you.</p>
            <p>And if I could repreſent your Effigies in the Front of theſe few
<pb facs="tcp:153725:6"/> Sheets, it ſhould be with your green Book in your Hand; gratefully receiving, modeſtly ſolliciting, and faithfully recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, the royal, noble, generous Contributions to this pious uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Work, which have amoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to about Eleven hundred Pounds, by your prudent Care and Induſtry, faithfully expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the erecting and adoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it.</p>
            <p>And I hereby, as much as in me lies, conſtitute you, who was for the greater part, receiver of their Money; Receiver-general in their Name, of all the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour I can do them, and the beſt Gratitude I can return them, for their ſo large and pious Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berality.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:153725:7"/>
            <p>And in this Inſcription which I make to you, as their Truſtee and Repreſentative, I dedicate theſe Papers to them all, with deepeſt Submiſſion, begging both their Pardon and Accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of ſo faint and diſpropor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable a return from the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of thoſe Divines who wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly beſtow our Pains amongſt them, till ſome of thoſe excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Perſons, of greater Ability, Name and Merit, be pleas'd to do it, with actual Performances, which may equal my Wiſhes and Deſires to do them Honour, and edify and inflame their Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>The late freſh Acceſſion of Princely Bounty, ſet as a Crown
<pb facs="tcp:153725:7"/> upon the Head of the preceding Charity, will not only be the laſting Ornament and Glory of the publick Table, you have expoſed in the Chappel to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Mans view, of all Monies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and expended, (to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Obloquy and Suſpicion in them who know you not, for thoſe who know you, do not need it;) But I hope is a good <hi>Omen,</hi> that in due time, it may be as conveniently endow'd as it is commodiouſly built, that there may be Wells of Salvation for the poor Neighbourhood all the Year; and if I may without imputation of Lightneſs, allude to St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Expreſſion, <hi>The Word may be preach'd in ſeaſon, and out of</hi> (Water) <hi>ſeaſon.</hi> Let not this unexpected Addreſs, be as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>welcome
<pb facs="tcp:153725:8"/> as unlook'd for; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let the Meanneſs of it cool the Reciprocation of that Eſteem and Friendſhip, which hath hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto been ſo obligingly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd to, Honoured Sir,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your cordial Friend, and willing Servant, <hi>ANTHONY WALKER.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>From my Lodgings near <hi>Tunbridg-Wells,</hi> 
                  <date>July 24. 1684.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:153725:8"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE Chriſtian Reader, Eſpecially Such as uſe the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Waters.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Good Reader;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S it is unqueſtionably the Duty and Interest of every Chriſtian, both to acquire and retain a deep and most ſerious ſenſe of God upon his own Heart; and as much as poſsibly he can, to
<pb facs="tcp:153725:9"/> impreſs the like upon his fellow Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</p>
            <p>So this Care is in a greater and more eminent degree incumbent upon Chriſt's Miniſters, whom he hath ſingled out and appointed to attend upon this most important Affair, and Buſineſs. And as no means are to be eſteem'd improper or ſuperfluous which God hath afforded or deſigned to this end; we ought our ſelves to learn, and teach others, from both the Books which God hath written for our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution and Inſtruction. Now theſe Books are that of the <hi>Creatures,</hi> and that of the <hi>Scriptures;</hi> of his Works, and of his Word; of his Providences, and of his Ordinances; of Nature and of Grace. Holy <hi>David</hi> joyns both theſe together in the <hi>19th Pſalm.</hi> He begins with the firſt, <hi>The Heavens declare
<pb facs="tcp:153725:9"/> the Glory of God, the Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhews his handy-work;</hi> to Verſe the 7th, where he proceeds to the ſecond, <hi>The Law of the Lord is perfect, converting the Soul: the Teſtimony of the Lord is ſure, making wiſe the ſimple; the Statutes of the Lord are right, rejoycing the Heart,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And as it cannot be denied, that both theſe great Volumes are full of the glorious Diſcoveries of God; ſo it muſt be confeſt, that the Waters are one of the faireſt and most legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Characters in which God's Name is written in the Book of Nature.</p>
            <p>The Rains, the Seas, the Rivers and the Fountains are as authentick witneſſes of the the Being, and of the Power, Wiſdom and Goodneſs of God, as any of thoſe other viſibles, which reflect the inviſible Perfections of the
<pb facs="tcp:153725:10"/> great Creator, Preſerver and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of all things. The Water<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are a natural Looking-glaſs, or Mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror; in them, <hi>Face anſwers to Face</hi> as the Wiſe-Man tells us, <hi>Prov. 27 19.</hi> And the Face of God may b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſeen reflected in them, as clearly and diſtinctly as in any of his providentia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Manifeſtations. And if the ordi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nary Properties of common Waters in their cleanſing, fructifying, ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, moistning, thirſt-quenching, and uniting Qualities, perform this ſo well; how much more do the Minera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Springs, by their extraordinary Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of healing, opening, purging, dulcifying, mollifying, ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and being most ſignally beneficial, loudly proclaim it? That it muſt argue great Stupidneſs not to obſerve it, and greater Ingratitude, yea Impiety, not to admire, love and
<pb facs="tcp:153725:10"/> praiſe him for them, who hath indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them with theſe Virtues, eſpecially in thoſe who uſe them, and have found them beneficial, and reap'd Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage by the uſe of them.</p>
            <p>Theſe things conſidered, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo many hundreds, yea thouſands in this and other Nations, yearly uſe ſuch Waters, both by Bathing and Potation; I cannot but wonder that nothing hath hitherto been publiſh'd, (that I could ever hear of) to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke, promote, or aſsist their Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from this particular Topick.</p>
            <p>Certainly if the Scale or Ladder of the Creatures be excellently fitted, to help the Minds aſcent to God; there is no round or ſtep, in all that Lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der more ſteady and firm (how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable ſoever Water be of it ſelf) than this of the Waters.</p>
            <p>Cardinal <hi>Bellarmin</hi> in the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe
<pb facs="tcp:153725:11"/> which he wrote <hi>(De aſcenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one mentis in Deum, per ſcalas rerum creaturum)</hi> not as an inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Diſputant, and peeviſh angry Controvertiſt, but as becomes a ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous pious Christian, in his <hi>Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> the Month he reſerved for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation and Devotion; with a calm and ſedate Spirit, reliſhing of no Heats, but thoſe decent and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable ones of Zeal Devotion, Admiration, Love and Thankfulneſs, hath one of the most conſiderable Chapters <hi>[Gradus Quartus]</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Subject; the ſum of which, for the ſake of Engliſh Readers, I have ſubjoyned amongst the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations and Prayers.</p>
            <p>I have therefore, (like <hi>Elihu</hi> in the Book of <hi>Job</hi>) provoked by the ſilence of thoſe who were fitter for it, adventured to adapt a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe,
<pb facs="tcp:153725:11"/> and add ſome Forms of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, Prayers and Thankſgivings, for the uſe of thoſe who attend the Mineral Waters. I heartily wiſh it had come a few days, or weeks, ſooner into my mind; that I might have had a little more time to have rendred it leſs incompleat.</p>
            <p>But I was loth wholly to ſlip this Water-ſeaſon, and therefore must ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture it abroad, ſo unpoliſht as it is: It may provoke ſome abler Hand: or, if it find but tolerable Acceptance, put me upon the trial, what I can do to its melioration, with ſome more lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and intention of thoughts. Much of it was written at the <hi>Wells</hi> (ſince my coming down this Seaſon, and all tranſcrib'd and ſent up ſheet by ſheet;) where, 'tis true, I had my Text daily before mine Eyes, but wanted my Books to comment on it.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:153725:12"/>
            <p>But tho 'twas partly writ at <hi>Tun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridg-Wells,</hi> and chiefly calculated for thoſe who uſe them; yet I had a Proſpect of their Benefit, who uſe other Mineral Waters, whether for inward or outward Diſtempers, by drinking, or by bathing.</p>
            <p>Amongst many other ſtrange Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> writes of two: One which is always full of Fiſh. <hi>De Geneſi ad lit. lib. 3. cap. 8.</hi> Another, that will light or kindle Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, tho its Water of it ſelf be cold. <hi>De Civ. Dei, lib. 21. cap. 5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And there is in <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> the like Fountain, (as I was lately here informed by a Perſon of Reputation, whoſe Teſtimony I do not in the least queſtion, he being an Eye-witneſs of it) that being ſtirr'd at the bottom, the ſteam of it will kindle Paper into a flame.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:153725:12"/>
            <p>If I can at theſe Fountains catch any Fiſh, in his ſenſe who ſaid, <hi>hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth you ſhall become Fiſhers of Men,</hi> I ſhall ſacrifice my Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, not to my Net, but unto Him at whoſe Word I let it down. For to fiſh for any thing elſe in ſuch an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking, I look upon as ſo unmanly, ſo unprieſtly, ſo unchriſtian; that I ſhould greatly deſpiſe my ſelf, ſhould I not deſpiſe ſo low, ſo muddy motives.</p>
            <p>And if I can bring Fire out of this Water, and kindle a Torch of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and inflame my own, and other Mens Devotion; the most aſcending of thoſe flames ſhall mount up to Him in humble Acknowledgments, who put the price into my hand, and gave me a heart in any meaſure to improve it. I will trouble you with no Apologies for my publiſhing theſe Papers, they ſeldom are free from Blame, never
<pb facs="tcp:153725:13"/> from ſiniſter Suſpicion; and ſuch Gildings oftner make them keck, for whom they are prepared, than the Pills themſelves they were deſigned to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
            <p>I thank God, I can ſincerely and with comfort ſay, I meant well, and aimed at the Glory of God, and the Edification of thoſe into whoſe hands they may come, how weakly ſoever I have performed: and this will yield me inward ſatisfaction, tho it ſhould render me in ſome Mens eyes, as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>'s dancing before the Ark rendred him in the eyes of <hi>Michal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude with theſe few Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts: and the <hi>firſt</hi> thing I ask of thee, good <hi>Reader,</hi> is, That thou wouldſt be like to God, in accepting of a willing mind.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly;</hi> If thou meeteſt here and there with an expreſsion out of the
<pb facs="tcp:153725:13"/> road of common phraſe, thou wouldſt not impute it to a vain affectation of hard words, but conſider, that the nature of the Subject conſtrain'd me to the uſe of them. For tho I am a very incompetent Judge of Oratory; yet I know that the moſt maſculine Eloquence is made up of plain expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive words (provided they be not ſlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly and rude) which ſuitably cloath the Notions of the Speaker, and apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly convey them to the Underſtandings of the Hearers. My Age allows me not to be a florid Speaker, had I ability to be ſo. I remember it was the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of <hi>Hortenſius,</hi> to be at once both green and gray, a verdant Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor in his fading, withered years. In a word, who-ever knows the Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory to which I ſpake, cannot deny, that ſpeaking as I did, and excuſing of my ſelf that I could ſpeak no better, needs no excuſe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:153725:14"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly;</hi> That if thou wilt not be ſo humble and ſo pious, as to be made better by it thy ſelf, yet be not ſo unjuſt and unkind as to reproach it, and thereby hinder others from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing benefited by it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly;</hi> If but one or two ſhall imploy ſome of thoſe vacant hours this time and place affords them, and ſhall thereby be helpt to pray to God, or to praiſe him; I entreat them to beg a Bleſsing on this Work, and him who is their Chriſtian Brother and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, for Jeſus ſake,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="erratum">
            <pb facs="tcp:153725:14"/>
            <p>Reader, Whereas the Title over the Pages are, <hi>A Sermon preached at Tunbridg,</hi> it ſhould have been, <hi>Two Sermons preached at Tunbridg-Wells.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:153725:15"/>
            <q xml:lang="lat">
               <bibl>Jo. Hen. Alſtedius Encyclop <hi>lib.</hi> 18. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. de Fontibus praecipuis. <hi>Peroratio Hydrographiae.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>HAEC eſt Hydrographia Marium, La<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cuum, Fluminum &amp; Fontium: Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> quatuor praecones Potentiae Sapientiae &amp; Cle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentiae Divinae: Surda qui praetervehitur a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, nè ille pluſquam ingratus: Nam ſiv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> quantitatem conſideres, illa eſt ſtupenda; ſiv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> qualitates illae ſunt utiliſſimae, ſive motum ille eſt admirandus. Quae omnia nos manu ducunt ad Dei Opt. Max. admirationem &amp; adorationem, cui ſoli ſit laus in ſolidum.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>The Seas, the Lakes, the Rivers, and the Fountains, are four loud Proclaimer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Divine Power, VViſdom, and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to which who ever turns a deaf Ear, he is worſe than ingrateful: For whether you conſider the Quantity, it is ſtupen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dous; or the Qualities, they are moſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial; or their Motion, it is wonderful. All which do lead us by the Hand to the Admiration and Adoration of that God, who is ſuperlatively Great and Good; to whom alone be everlaſting Praiſes.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:153725:15"/>
            <head>A SERMON ON
<q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>REV. 14.7.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>— And worſhip him that made the Fountains of Waters.</p>
               </q>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Words I have read, and the Place where we are, have ſo agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able an Aſpect upon each other, that it needs no farther Intimation, to ſhew what I deſign, or aim at, in the choice of them.</p>
            <p>Nor will an <hi>Apology</hi> for my fixing on them be more neceſſary, to any who will allow (and who is not
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:153725:16"/> aſham'd to diſallow it?) that the Wiſdom and Example of our Maſter <hi>CHRIST,</hi> who is the eſſential Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the only wiſe God, is the beſt and moſt Authentick <hi>Copy</hi> for all his Servants to write after.</p>
            <p>For nothing is more notorious, than that moſt of his Sermons were occaſional, preach'd upon viſible Texts; Improvements of earthly Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, to heavenly Purpoſes. A Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod which inſenſibly prepares the Auditors, and innocently charms them to Attention, without beſpeaking it. Such was that in the 4th of St. <hi>John</hi> to the Woman of <hi>Samaria,</hi> who came to draw Water at <hi>Jacob's Well,</hi> to ſtir up her deſire after that living Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which he gives, and of which <hi>who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever drinks, ſhall thirſt no more: but it becomes in him a Well of Water, ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up unto Everlaſting Life.</hi> And ſuch was that in the ſixth of the ſame Evangeliſt, <hi>of the Bread of Life, the true Bread which comes down from Heaven,</hi> which he exhorts them to labour for, from his obſerving how
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:153725:16"/> they followed him, becauſe he had fed them with the multiply'd Loaves.</p>
            <p>I ſhall ſupercede more Inſtances, leſt I ſeem indecently to ſuſpect your obſerving that, which is ſo obvious and remarkable, that he who runs may read it.</p>
            <p>But it may poſſibly more need ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, that I have pitch'd upon a Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage in that Book, which partly by its enigmatical, prophetical Stile, and partly by the Miſadventures of thoſe who have adventur'd to unriddle it, ſeems like that little Book in the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel's Hand, <hi>Chap.</hi> 5.1, 2, 3. of which none on Earth have been found wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to unlooſe the Seals, and bleſs the World with a clear Interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it. But I hope this modeſt ſhort Reply, may ſuffice to remove that Prejudice: What St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> obſerv'd of the whole Scripture is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicable to this part of it, the <hi>Apoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyps;</hi> Tho there be depths in which the Elephant may ſwim, there are alſo Shallows, in which the Lamb may wade. And tho its Prophecies are ſo
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:153725:17"/> profound, we want a Line to ſound and fathom them; and muſt wait till Events and Completions, (their beſt and only infallible Interpreters) ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them intelligible and plain; and which might be written, not to gratify our Curioſity with the fore-Knowledg of what is future, but to confirm their Faith who ſhall live to ſee them fulfill'd, that they who ſee them come to paſs may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, as our Saviour ſpeaks on the like account, St. <hi>John</hi> 14.29. Yet are there many doctrinal Truths, and moral practical Duties, in this very Book, moſt eaſy, plain and clear, and no where to be found more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligibly expreſt, or more poſitively aſſerted: Such as are the Divinity of Chriſt: The truth and efficacy of his Death and Reſurrection: that there are Eternal Rewards and Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for good and bad Men: That the true God is only to be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped; that he is to be adored and ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated for his wonderful Works, and for that Wiſdom, Power and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:153725:17"/> Goodneſs, which ſhines forth in them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I might give many more Inſtances of the like kind, and ſay of them all, as St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> doth expreſly of many Paſſages in this Book; <hi>Tanta lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce dicta ſunt, ut nulla debeamus in literis ſacris quaerere vel legere manifeſta, ſi haec putaverimus obſcura.</hi> See <hi>De Civitate Dei lib.</hi> 20. <hi>cap.</hi> 17. They are ſpoken with ſo much Light and Clearneſs, that nothing in ſacred Writ is to be eſteemed plain and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy, if theſe Truths be reckoned ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure and unintelligible.</p>
            <p>But I need no other, no clearer Inſtance than this Verſe, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains the Sum of the everlaſting <hi>Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,</hi> which the Angel, whom St. <hi>John</hi> ſaw in the preceding Verſe, flying in the midſt of Heaven, had to preach to all Nations, Kindreds, Tongues, and People; and he executes and diſcharges his Truſt with great Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs and Boldneſs, with a loud Voice, that all might hear, in <hi>Iſaiah</hi>'s Phraſe, a Voice lift up like a Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet. The main deſign and ſcope of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153725:18"/> his preaching is, to call the World from their Idolatry, to the Worſhip and Service of the true God only; and to ſhew, that in this conſiſts the Life, the Soul, the Spirit of true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, the Sum and Subſtance of the Goſpel, to admit no Competitors with God in the matter of his Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
            <p>The whole Sermon is reduceable to two Points; The Duty exhorted to, and the Motive by which that Duty is preſt. Both which, are in their kind, of the higheſt Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; no Duty can be more neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and indiſpenſible, no Motive can be more cogent and irreſiſtible. <hi>The hour of his Judgment is come;</hi> 'tis ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of in the preſent Tenſe, to ſhew the immutable certainty; ſhall as ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come, as if it were come already. And he that conſiders this, and is not awakened by it, is not reſtrained from worſhipping what is not God, and provoked effectually to ſerve and worſhip him, hath an Heart harder than an Anvil, or an Adamant.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:153725:18"/>
            <p>The Duty is one for Subſtance, but hath three Parts or Degrees, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratory or ſubſervient to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Fear God.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Give him Glory.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>Worſhip him.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>To which laſt is added a moſt au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt Periphaſis to deſcribe him, <hi>viz. Who made the Heaven, the Earth, the Sea and the Fountains.</hi> The firſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares for the other two.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Fear of God is the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation and Corner-ſtone of all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. Both <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solomon</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure us, that 'tis the Beginning, the Head, the Top of Wiſdom, even of that by which Men become wiſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Salvation.</p>
            <p>'Tis the Character of the worſt of Men, <hi>to have no fear of God before their Eyes.</hi> An awful Dread of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Majeſty is the greateſt and beſt Reſtraint and Barrier againſt all Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety. Where this is remov'd or broken down, the boldeſt Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153725:19"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:153725:19"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:153725:20"/> flows in as a Flood, as a Torrent, and bears down all before it. When carnal Security hath eraſed the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of a Divine Being, there's no Impiety ſo bad, and boundleſs, into which Men will not run and ruſh. And little <hi>hope</hi> remains, that inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and revealed Religion ſhould a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, where the very Seeds and Roots of all natural Religion are choak'd and pluck'd up. They will never give God Glory, who do not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg his Being and Providence, and retain not a <hi>deep</hi> Awe, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Veneration for him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond ſtep or degree in the injoyned Duty is, <hi>Give Glory to him.</hi> This is the Superſtructure, to be next erected, and built upon it, when and where the Foundation of it, his Fear, is laid and well ſettled.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Glory</hi> is Excellency manifeſted. And to give God Glory, is to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg the excellent Perfections of his Nature, with Affections and Actions ſutable to thoſe acknowledged
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:153725:20"/> Perfections, and to praiſe him for them.</p>
            <p>Now both becauſe this is expreſly call'd the everlaſting Goſpel, which is the glad Tidings of Salvation to loſt Mankind by Jeſus Chriſt, which the Angel (that is the Miniſters of the Goſpel) was to preach: and alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>the Light of the Knowledg of the Glory of God, ſhines in the Face of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 2 Cor. 4.6. that is, the Goſpel, and is therein moſt clearly manifeſted. We give Glory to God moſt eminently, moſt acceptably, by believing and obeying the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>That's the true Tabernacle in which his Glory dwells in the World. He hath made all his Glory paſs before him, in the Accompliſhment of Mans Salvation by his Son's Mediation, which he ſtrives with us by his Spirit to perſwade and draw us to accept and improve: Herein he hath gloriouſly diſplayed his unſearchable Wiſdom, his infinite Power, the inexhauſtible Treaſuries of his Grace and Mercy, and the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutability of his Truth and Faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:153725:21"/> which cannot ſhrink or ſhake, but ſtands faſter than the ancient Hills. And we then give him the Glory he expects, when by obeying the Goſpel we openly profeſs, that we eſteem him to be ſuch, as the Goſpel hath declared him to be; ſo wiſe, ſo great, ſo good, ſo true, as he is worthy to be acknowledged, for what he hath done for us in and by the Goſpel of his Son.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third degree or ſtep in the injoyned Duty is—<hi>And worſhip him which made the Heavens, and the Earth, and the Sea, and the Fountains of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> In this third Branch he calls the World from their Superſtitions to the Worſhip of the only true God, of whom he gives a moſt Auguſt Deſcription by his incommunicable Works, and excludes and ſhuts out all Competitors from being worſhipped, who cannot ſhew their Title to it, by ſuch ſtupendous Works as theſe. And as in the firſt he laid the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, and in the ſecond raiſed the Superſtructure, ſo in this third he ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:153725:21"/> its ſtanding; Nothing ſo much threatning the over-throw and ruine of God's Glory as giving religious Worſhip to any thing that by nature is not God.</p>
            <p>But our preſent Concern and Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs permits me not to graſp at the whole of this Angelick Sermon; nor allows me to enquire into the ſcope, and give the Explication of the whole Prophetick Scene, but confines me to the third Branch, and even in that, excludes a great part of the Periphra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis, by which he who may, and muſt be worſhipped, is deſcribed; that is, <hi>He that made the Heaven, Earth and Sea:</hi> which is a Character of the true God, ſo proper, ſo peculiar, ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſive of all Competitors, ſo intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible, ſo awful and affecting, that we meet with it every where moſt fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently in holy Writ, in the Law, the Prophets, the Pſalms, and the New Teſtament.</p>
            <p>But my own choice and deſign, and I ſuppoſe your Expectation, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits me to the laſt Syllable of this
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153725:22"/> glorious Name — <hi>The Fountains of Waters,</hi> which when I have joyn'd to the preceptive Words in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, by an innocent omiſſion of the intermediate, comes to this, — <hi>Worſhip him that made the Fountains of Waters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which Words we have three Particulars to be obſerved.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A Deſcription of the Object of Religious Adoration, which may and which muſt be worſhipped, <hi>Him that made the Fountains of Waters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. An imply'd Reaſon of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring us to give ſuch Worſhip to him: Becauſe he made the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of Waters.</p>
            <p n="3">3. An actual injoyning the Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this Homage to him, under that Notion, and upon that account: <hi>Worſhip him who made the Fountains,</hi> and do it for that reaſon, becauſe he made them.</p>
            <p>Now for the clearer underſtanding, and more uſeful improvement of theſe Particulars, and to demonſtrate the argumentative force of this Reaſon,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:153725:22"/> that he who made the Fountains muſt therefore be worſhipped, I ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce all I have to ſpeak to them to this eaſy method.</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. To enquire what is the ſole Object, adequate Reaſon, and right Notion of Religious Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</item>
               <item>II. Who made, and in a ſhort Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, how he made the Fountains.</item>
               <item>III. Why the Angel propounds him to be worſhipp'd under this Notion, <hi>Maker of the Fountains;</hi> and how it may appear that this is a good and ſufficient Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to oblige us to it.</item>
               <item>IV. Draw practical Inferences from the whole, proper to us at this Place and Time.</item>
            </list>
            <p>I begin with the firſt Inquiry, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Object, Reaſon and right Notion of Religious Worſhip.</p>
            <p>The true God is the ſole Object of Religious Worſhip. <hi>Thou ſhalt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:153725:23"/> the Lord thy God, and him only ſhalt thou ſerve.</hi> And the adequate reaſon of his Worſhip, is, becauſe he is God, that is, a Being abſolutely perfect, which is the beſt Notion of God. A Being which hath infinite Wiſdom, Power, Goodneſs, and full Authority and Dominion over us; Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient Ability, and moſt gracious Willingneſs to help us. And there are as many Reaſons for his Worſhip, as there are Proofs and Manifeſtations of theſe his adorable Perfections, either in the Works of Creation and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, as he is God of Nature; or in the Work of Redemption, by the Renovation and Salvation of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, as he is the God of all Grace. Now, tho I do not equallize theſe Reaſons, and affirm all of them to be of the ſame Evidence and Cogency: Yet I ſay, whatever Works of Nature or of Grace, manifeſt theſe and the like adorable Perfections to be in him, render him, for that reaſon, a ſuitable Object of Adoration, and bind us to perform it to him.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:153725:23"/>
            <p>Now the Worſhip we owe, and muſt pay him, is ſometimes taken largely for the whole of true Religion, by which we expect Salvation. <hi>In co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendo rectè Deo una ſalus eſt.</hi> St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin.</hi> Our whole Salvation depends upon our right worſhipping of God. And again, To love God with all our Heart, and Soul, and Strength, and to commend God as much as poſſibly we can to the Love of our Neighbour. <hi>Hic eſt Dei cultus, haec vera Religio, haec recta Pietas, haec tantùm Deo debita Servitus. De Civ. Dei,</hi> lib. 5. c. 4. This is God's Worſhip, this is true Religion, this is right Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, this is the only Service due to God. So that to worſhip God, is to be truly godly, and ſincerely religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, good in good earneſt, and to pay him all the Service our holy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion exacts from us towards him.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly; The Notion of Worſhip is more confined and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained, and is either internal or external.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:153725:24"/>1. Internal, again, is either the Act of the Mind, Reaſon and Judgment: Or of the Heart, Soul, Will and Affections.</p>
            <p>In the firſt reſpect, as it is an Act of our Reaſon, Mind and Underſtanding, it implies our knowing and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging his Superiority and full Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over us, and eſteeming him a Being ſo fully and abſolutely perfect, that in fruition of him, we may be compleatly and abſolutely happy and bleſſed. <hi>Solus ille colendus eſt, quo ſolo fruens beatus eſt cultor ejus: &amp; quo ſolo non fruens omnis mens miſera eſt, qualibet re alia perfruatur. Aug.</hi> lib. 20. <hi>contra Fauſtum Manich.</hi> cap. 5.</p>
            <p>He only is to be worſhipped, by injoying whom alone his Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per is made bleſſed, and by the want of whom alone every Soul is miſerable what ever elſe he doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond reſpect, as it is an Act of our Will and Affections, it implies our choice of him, and adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to him, by loving, fearing, truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:153725:24"/> and delighting in him, ſubmitting to him, obeying and imitating of him, as a Being, which is the chiefeſt Good, Great, True, Juſt, Holy, and the perfect Idea of all moſt amiable and deſirable Excellencies. <hi>Optimus cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus quem colis imitari,</hi> ſaith <hi>Lactanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> that is the moſt acceptable Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, to imitate and endeavour to be like him whom we worſhip. <hi>Pietas cultus Dei eſt, nec colitur ille niſi aman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, Aug. Epiſt.</hi> 120. No Worſhip is accepted but what proceeds from Love.</p>
            <p n="2">2. External Worſhip is that which expreſſes the inward Frame and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of our Minds and Souls, by apt and ſutable ſigns of bodily Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, as bowing our Knees, unco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering our Heads, Proſtration of our Bodies, confeſſing of him, praying to him, giving him Thanks with our Mouths, and performing all the parts of his inſtituted Worſhip according to his Will and Word: for not only the ſecond Commandment requires this, but the Light of Nature; for
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:153725:25"/> 
               <hi>Socrates,</hi> a heathen Philoſopher, could ſay, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>numquem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Deum ſic coli opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet quomodo ſe ipſe colendum praeceperit,</hi> Every God ought to be worſhipp'd, as he commands himſelf to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipp'd.</p>
            <p>So that the Worſhip of God rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to, and is to be performed by, the whole inward and outward Man, and we muſt thereby <hi>glorify him in our Bodies and our Spirits, which are both his,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.20. firſt with our Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits and Minds, knowing, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging and eſteeming him as a Being abſolutely perfect and all-ſufficient, moſt able and willing to help and make us happy.</p>
            <p>Secondly; Loving him, fearing him, truſting in him, as moſt good, and great, and true, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly; With our Bodies, by all thoſe reverential Geſtures, which are proper Signs and Indications of the right Frame and Diſpoſition of our Hearts towards him; and this laſt ſeems to be implied in the very No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Greek Word here
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:153725:25"/> uſed προσκυνήσατε, which is (as ſome ſay) derived from the Verb κύω, <hi>oſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor,</hi> to kiſs, becauſe it was the Cuſtom of the Eaſtern Nations to worſhip by kiſſing the Hand, the Knee, <hi>&amp;c. Pſal.</hi> 2. <hi>Kiſs the Son,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13.2. <hi>Let the Men that ſacrifice, kiſs the Calves.</hi> Or elſe from κυὼν <hi>Canis,</hi> a Dog, from the humble Poſture of a Spaniel lying at and licking of his Maſters Feet. For things in their own Nature low and mean, may afford Alluſions to, and be Illuſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of, matters of the higheſt and greateſt moment and importance. It implies a willing Acknowledgment of his Heighth, and our Lowneſs; his Dominion, and our Subjection; his All-ſufficiency, and our Indigency.</p>
            <p>Thus much for the firſt Particular propounded, the Sum of which is this, That the true God muſt be worſhipp'd with our Spirit, Soul, and Body; and whatever proves him to be ſuch, is a good and ſufficient Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to engage us to perform ſuch Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to him, whether it proceed from
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:153725:26"/> him as the God of Nature, or of Grace.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The ſecond thing propounded to be inquired into was, Who made the Fountains of Waters, and how he made them? that we may both try and prove his Title to Religious Adoration upon that account.</p>
            <p>The Solution of the firſt Branch of this Enquiry, is eaſy by the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Divinity; but the ſecond is more difficult by the Principles of Philoſophy.</p>
            <p>To the firſt therefore I may anſwer briefly, The true God made them: which the holy Scriptures both aſſert and prove.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They aſſert it. <hi>Prov.</hi> 8. ſeems both to be very expreſs, and very em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phatical: for there <hi>Solomon</hi> brings in Wiſdom, that is, Chriſt, the eſſential Wiſdom of God, aſſerting and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his own eternal Being, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Subſiſtence. And he proves it by a double Medium, or two Arguments; firſt, becauſe he was
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:153725:26"/> before God's oldeſt Works.</p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe he was preſent at the making of them.</p>
            <p>The firſt he does in five Verſes, from the 22d to 26, incluſively. Verſ. 22. <hi>The Lord poſſeſſed me in the beginning of his Ways, before his Works of old.</hi> Then he enumerates and gives Inſtances of thoſe Works: as the Earth, Verſ. 23. <hi>I was ſet up from everlaſting, from the beginning, or ever the Earth was.</hi> Next in the Depth and Fountains, Verſ. 24. <hi>When there were no Depths was I brought forth, when there were no Fountains abounding with Water.</hi> Where the Earth, the Depths, and the Fountains of Waters, are expreſly call'd his Works, yea the moſt ancient, the earlieſt, the firſt-born of his Works, which he glories in being known by, as the Father and Maker of them.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Argument by which he proves the Eternity of his Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence is, That he was preſent with God when he prepared the Heavens, ſtabliſhed the Clouds above, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:153725:27"/> ſtrengthned the Fountains of the deep: where the making the Fountains is as directly aſcribed to him, as the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the Heavens. This place is ſo full and clear, it might ſuffice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, with the Text, without adding more.</p>
            <p>The Spirit of Chriſt, ſpeaking by the Mouth of <hi>Solomon,</hi> gives us aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, that his Father made the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains.</p>
            <p>And <hi>David</hi> ſaith no leſs: for, ſpeaking of God, he ſaith, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.10. <hi>He ſendeth forth his Springs into the Valleys, which run among the Hills; they are his Springs, and he ſends them forth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pſal. 107.33, &amp; 35. <hi>He turneth the Rivers into a Wilderneſs, and the Water-Springs into dry Ground.</hi> Then again, <hi>He turneth the Wilderneſs into a ſtanding-water, and dry Ground into Water-Springs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Iſa. 35.6, 7. <hi>In the Wilderneſs ſhall Waters break out, and Streams in the Deſert; and the parched Land ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Pool, and the thirſty Land
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:153725:27"/> Springs of Water.</hi> And let it be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd and granted, that theſe Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions are figurative, and ſignify the pouring out of his Spirit in the Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Comforts of it, upon deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late and weary Souls: yet the thing muſt be firſt true in the literal and natural Sence, that God can and doth perform ſuch things in the courſe of Nature, and Providence, and can and will do what is like them, in the Operations of his Grace. Again,</p>
            <p>Iſa. 41.18. <hi>I will open Rivers in high places, and Fountains in the midſt of the Valleys; I will make the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs a Pool of Water, and the dry Land Springs of Water.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in the Canticle, <hi>Benedicite om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia opera,</hi> commonly called the <hi>Song of the three Children,</hi> which in our Liturgy is appointed to be ſaid or ſung after the firſt Leſſon at Morning Prayer, <hi>Te Deum,</hi> or that, and is taken out of the Additions to <hi>Dan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el;</hi> Where all the <hi>Magnalia,</hi> the ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Works of God are reckoned up, and excited to bleſs the Lord, which
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:153725:28"/> is to provoke Men to bleſs God for them. There we find Fountains or Wells, in the Liſt or Catalogue of thoſe famous Works of God. <hi>O ye Wells, bleſs ye the Lord, praiſe him, and magnify him for ever.</hi> And I wiſh that in this place at leaſt that <hi>Canticle</hi> were ſometimes read, as the Liturgy ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>points; for not only that Verſicle is very proper, but the whole very warming and enflaming.</p>
            <p>I ſtay not to deſcant upon every Scripture I have cited, nor to ſhew wherein their Strength lay, to prove what I produc'd them for, becauſe I ſuppoſe ſuch Evidence to accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny them, that 'tis needleſs, and would be ſuperfluous. I may ſubjoin Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments to prove that God made the Fountains, though very tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Our Text ſuppoſes it, and takes it for granted. And both this Text and the 8th of <hi>Proverbs,</hi> and many other Scriptures, rank them in the ſame Order and Series with the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, the Earth, and the Sea, to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:153725:28"/> ſignifie that God is as undoubtedly the Maker of thoſe, as of theſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The true God made the Waters above the Heavens; He is the Father of the Rain, and he begets the drops of Dew. <hi>Job</hi> 38.28. And by parity of Reaſon, He makes the Waters under the Earth, and the Miſts, the Vapors, and the Springs that riſe from thence.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He makes the miraculous extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Fountains, and Streams that flow from them: as that, <hi>Exod.</hi> 17.6. <hi>Behold, I will ſtand before thee there up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Rock, and thou ſhalt ſmite the Rock, and there ſhall come forth Waters out of it.</hi> Which the Pſalmiſt aſcribes to God, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 78.15. <hi>He clave the Rock in the Wilderneſs, and gave them Drink as out of the great Depths.</hi> And <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105.41. <hi>He opened the Rock, and the Waters guſhed out: they ran in dry pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces like a River.</hi> And the other Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains are the effects of the ſame Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and are accounted leſs miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, only becauſe they are more common.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:153725:29"/>4. God is the great <hi>Artificer</hi> and Maker of Univerſal Nature. <hi>He that made all things is God.</hi> And what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſecond cauſes he hath appointed and conſtituted, as inſtrumental to produce the Fountains, he is as truly the Maker of them ſtill, as he is the Maker of every one of us, tho we had Fathers who begat us, and Mothers in whoſe Wombs we were all formed. Job 31.15. <hi>Did not he that made me in the Womb, make him, and did not one faſhion us in the Womb? Cauſa cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſae eſt cauſa cauſati.</hi> He is as truly to be intitled to what he produceth medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately, as to his moſt immediate Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Laſtly; The Scripture, which is exceeding jealous of the Glory of God in point of Worſhip, and can endure Competitors and Copartners, leſs than a King in his Throne, or an Huſband in his Bed, (<hi>My Glory will I not give to another,</hi> Iſa. 42.8.) yet allows and requires the Glory of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Worſhip to be given to him that made the Fountains; which is an
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:153725:29"/> infallible Inference, that by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures Teſtimony, he that made them, is the true God.</p>
            <p>This may ſuffice to prove that God made the Fountains. But to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate how he made them, is more dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult.</p>
            <p>'Tis a noble and delightful, but withall a buſy and perplexed Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, both amongſt Divines and Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers, concerning the Origine of Fountains, their various uſeful Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, and how they became inriched with them; their Perennity, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant flowing for ſo many Ages; their vaſt depth in the loweſt Bowels of the Earth, where they are often found; and again, their ſtrange aſcent and heighth, and breaking out, as they ſometimes do, in the higheſt Tops and Summities of Mountains, and many more of no leſs difficult Solution.</p>
            <p>But tho the ſearch into theſe things be exceeding pleaſant to inquiſitive Minds, and it might not be unwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to many of you to diſcuſs them; Yet it is not ſo proper for the Pulpit,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:153725:30"/> as the Schools; and would not well become a Diſcourſe, which deſigns to miniſter to Devotion, rather than to gratify your Curioſity, and delight your Fancies.</p>
            <p>Yet that I may not tantalize your Minds by a meer ſtarting of Queſtions, nor diſoblige you by a vexing Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointment, I will firſt refer you to thoſe Authors, who by what they ſay themſelves, and by directing you to near an hundred more, may, if not ſatisfy the curious, yet weary the moſt inquiſitive and induſtrious: and having done that, tho I wade not through, ſhall dip a little into theſe Queſtions.</p>
            <p>In that Age, which was <hi>Ingeniorum ferax,</hi> about our Saviour's Birth, when it ſeem'd good to God to raiſe up in, and adorn the World with Wits of the firſt Magnitude, to uſher in and attend upon the Incarnation of his eternal Wiſdom, ſuch as <hi>Virgil, Tully, Ovid, Horace;</hi> liv'd <hi>L. Annaeus, Seneca,</hi> that excellent, and I may ſay, Divine Moraliſt, and learned natural
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:153725:30"/> Philoſopher, who hath fine Diſcourſes on this Subject, <hi>lib.</hi> 3. of his natural Queſtions. And few have gone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond him, notwithſtanding the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of coming ſo long in time behind him.</p>
            <p>The laborious and diligent <hi>Poloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> Johan. Jonſtonus, <hi>Thaumatographia naturalis. Claſis ſecundae Capit.</hi> 4. <hi>de origine Fontium,</hi> where you may meet with the Epitome of what our own Country-man, <hi>Tho. Lydiat,</hi> hath writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten moſt accutely on this Subject.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Voetius</hi> in his ſelect Diſputations, both diſcuſſes the Queſtions relating to this matter, and gives copious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences. <hi>Corn. a Lapide,</hi> on <hi>Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtes</hi> 1.7. is large in both diſputing it himſelf, and in referring to the Greek and Latin Fathers and Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers. What <hi>Alſtedius</hi> ſays is in no wiſe deſpicable, <hi>Encyclop. lib.</hi> 13. <hi>Phyſicorum, part</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. <hi>Regula</hi> 3. and <hi>part</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 2. and <hi>lib.</hi> 18. <hi>Hydrograph. cap.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>I forbear to name <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and thoſe who follow the Tract of the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:153725:31"/> old Philoſophy, or <hi>Carteſius</hi> and his Sectators in the new; becauſe they are well known to thoſe, who can, or will puruſe them, and are referred to (the firſt epecially) in thoſe I have nam'd already; and tho it may ſeem an ignorant or culpable Omiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to take no notice of the ingenious Mr. <hi>Thomas Burnet</hi>'s new Theory of the Earth, both in Latin and Engliſh, I ſhall have occaſion to mention him hereafter.</p>
            <p>But not to tire my ſelf and you with naming more, the Engliſh Reader may meet with more Satisfaction, than he could expect in ſo few Pages from any other Pen, in the acurate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly learned, and truly great Man, the Author of <hi>Origines Sacrae, lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. §. 6. whoſe great Happineſs it is to ſpeak much in a little, and be ſhort without Obſcurity, at once conciſe and perſpicuous, brief and clear.</p>
            <p>And having before, I hope, ſatisfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, prov'd that God made the Fountains: Let me briefly touch the Way, the Manner, the Art by which
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:153725:31"/> that great and wiſe Artificer per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd this Work, produc'd and made them. And to diſmiſs and wave the reſt, there are three Opinions, which almoſt all that write on this Subject, chiefly inſiſt upon.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt; Some aſcribe the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine of Fountains, to the Tranſmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Elements; Air and Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours, ſay they, getting into the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns and hollow Receſſes of the Earth, are by the Coldneſs of the Rocks and Stones condenſed and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into Waters, as we ſee in Vaults and Cellers; the Stone Walls will ſtand with Drops, eſpecially when the Air is thick and moiſt. This O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion glories in no leſs Author, than him who was the great Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary of Nature, <hi>Ariſtotle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This, I confeſs, may do ſomething, produce ſome little Rills and fainter Springs; but the Objection againſt it ſeems rationally ſtrong, and unanſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; as to more noble Fountains, which flow <hi>ubere venâ,</hi> from the vaſt quantities of Waters they ſend forth, which we
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:153725:32"/> cannot conceive, how this means a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone can poſſibly ſupply and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Others ſuppoſe them to ariſe from the falling of Rain, and diſſolution of Snow, ſoaking into the Bowels of the Earth, and when it ſinks into the hollow Caverns of it, glides through them, till it finds ſome vent, and makes a Spring at its Eruption, or place of breaking forth. And tho there may be ſome colour for this in ſome Times and Places, as near the Alps, yet this is beſet with greater Difficulties than the former: from the exceeding depth of many ſubter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raneous Waters, and the Times and Places, where the Rains and Snows, are none, or few and ſmall, and yet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford both plenteous and conſtant Fountains.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Therefore the third and beſt Opinion, and which is beſet with eaſieſt Objections, is, That Fountains ariſe from the Sea, and from vaſt Stores and Treaſuries of Water, made by God, and reſerved under ground, in
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:153725:32"/> vaſt capacious Ciſterns and Cellars, for this end and uſe.</p>
            <p>And this Opinion fairly claims and pleads both the patronage of Scripture, and the ſuffrage of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            <p>Firſt, of Scripture, which often mentions the great Abyſs, the Deep, the Depths, (the ſame with <hi>Plato's Barathron</hi>) as the Womb and Mother of Springs. Gen. 7.11. <hi>The Fountains of the great Deep were broken up,</hi> to make the Flood. And again, chap. 8.2. <hi>The Fountains of the Deep were ſtopped.</hi> And <hi>Job</hi> 38.16. they are call'd <hi>the Springs of the Sea.</hi> Pſal. 33.7. <hi>He layeth up the Depth in Store-houſes,</hi> to be thus broach'd and iſſued forth. Eccleſ. 1.7. <hi>All the Rivers run into the Sea, and yet the Sea is not full: unto the place from whence the Rivers come, thither they return again.</hi> They come from the Sea through the Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of the Earth; and return unto it, through the Chanels in the Surface of it. Fountains are the Mouths by which the Sea and great Abyſs vomit,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:153725:33"/> and caſt forth thoſe mighty Streams, the Rivers.</p>
            <p>And with the Scripture-Teſtimony concur <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Seneca,</hi> and other Naturaliſts. And the Sum of this Opinion is, That there are vaſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious Quantities of Water reſerved under ground, in huge Caverns and hollow Receptacles: and that the Sea hath alſo in the ſides and bottom of it, either looſe ſpungy Earth, which the Waters eaſily penetrate, and ſoak through: Or elſe large <hi>Oſtia,</hi> wide Clefts and gaping Orifices, and Whirl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits; by which it empties out, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burdens it ſelf of its ſuperfluous Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: without which Evacuations, and diſcharging of it ſelf of that vaſt maſs of Waters, which flow continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally into it by ſo many Rivers, it muſt neceſſarily and unavoidably over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flow the Earth, which is moſt obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly manifeſt in the <hi>Caſpian</hi> Sea, which hath no viſible Intercourſe with, or outlet into the main Ocean, and yet the Waters which run into it from the might <hi>Volga</hi> in one Year,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:153725:33"/> were ſufficient to drown that part of the World, ſhould it not have ſecret conveyances and ways of Evacuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to prevent its over-flowing.</p>
            <p>Some have ingeniouſly compar'd this <hi>Terraqueous</hi> Globe, to a great Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal: the vaſt Abyſs is as the Heart or Liver (or the Blood-bowl in the ruſtick Phraſe); theſe Waters are the Blood; the hollow Caverns under Ground, and the Chanels of the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers in the Surface, are as the Arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Veins, by which this Blood circulates, and where its <hi>Apertures,</hi> and places of breaking forth are, there are the Springs and Fountains, which reſemble the Orifices upon the prick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or opening of a Vein by Phlebo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>romy.</p>
            <p>And whereas the Sea is ſalt, and many Fountains freſh; this account is given, That God at firſt made all the Waters ſweet and freſh, and thoſe vaſt ſtores treaſured up in the Bowels of the Earth retain thoſe their primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Qualities; tho in great Wiſdom, he after made the Sea ſalt, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:153725:34"/> its Putrefaction by Stagnation; and to make it fitter for the Nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of living Creatures in it, and more commodious for Navigation, the ſtrength of the ſalt Water bearing thoſe Veſſels of Burden, which were it freſh, would ſink to the bottom with their own weight: an Egg will ſwim in ſtrong Brine.</p>
            <p>And for the Sea-Water, which paſſes out, as aforeſaid, the fixed Salt is ſtrained off by Percollation: and the volatil Salt, partly by Evaporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the ſubterraneous Fires, and partly by mixing with the ſweet Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in the bowels of the Earth, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of thoſe made of tranſmuted Air and Vapours; and farther by Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of Rain which ſoaks in, and diſſolved Snows which mingle with it, it becomes lympid, ſweet, and wholſome.</p>
            <p>And by paſſing through different Soils or Minerals, as Gold, Silver, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timony, Copper, Lead, Tin, and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, Vitriol, Nitre, Sulphur, Allom, and God only knows how many
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:153725:34"/> more, it is impregnated by them, imbibes their Properties and Vertues; beſides what uſeful Qualities God may in his kind Providence infuſe into them and communicate immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately, to render them uſeful and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial to Mankind: of which no account can be given, but the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of him, who doth what ever he pleaſeth in Heaven, in Earth, and <hi>all deep places,</hi> and worketh all things according to his own good Pleaſure.</p>
            <p>But to ſum up and reduce to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, this more lax Diſcourſe, I will lay down theſe following Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. 'Tis demonſtrable by Scripture, that God made the Fountains.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He made them not as a neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but a voluntary Agent: they are not the product of his Nature, but his Will.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Knowledg we have of the Origine of them as to their ſecond and immediate cauſes, is not certain
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:153725:35"/> and demonſtrative, but only probable and conjectural.</p>
            <p n="4">4. 'Tis probable ſome are made, and others are encreas'd by Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutation, or change of groſſer and moiſter Air and Vapours into Water.</p>
            <p n="5">5. 'Tis very probable, that the wiſe Builder of Univerſal Nature hath ſo diſpos'd and faſhioned the whole Syſtem of this Terraqueous Globe, that there are in it, as it were Furnaces of ſubterraneous Fires: and vaſt hollow Caves and winding Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anders, not unlike to natural Stills, and Alymbecks, and Retorts, which turn ſalt Waters into Vapours, and then change both thoſe Vapours, and others ſuckt into the Chinks and Caverns of the Earth, from the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bient Air and Miſts, into ſweet and wholſome Waters.</p>
            <p n="6">6. 'Tis poſſible that ſome Springs ariſe, or at leaſt may be augmented (ſuch as are vulgarly call'd Land-ſprings) from Rains and diſſolved Snows, ſoaking into, and reſerved in the prepared void Places or Caverns
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:153725:35"/> of the Earth, which fail and dry up the times of Drought.</p>
            <p n="7">7. 'Tis of all Opinions moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, that the principal Fountains have their Origen from the Sea, and great Abyſs, or huge ſtore and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury of Waters, made and reſerved in the deep Cellars of the Earth, for that very end and purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="8">8. 'Tis very likely that the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain-Waters receive their ſeveral uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Qualities from the various Soils and Minerals through which they glide and imbibe, and are impregna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by their different Properties, while they are percollated and ſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed through them; and become be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial for Bathing or Potation, out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward or inward Application.</p>
            <p n="9">9. 'Tis probable that beſides the ſecond Cauſes, God makes uſe of (at leaſt ſo far as any Philoſophy hitherto hath, or can give a full and ſatisfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry account) God doth impreſs upon them and communicate to them im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, many of thoſe uſeful Qualities, by which they become
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:153725:36"/> ſo beneneficial to Mankind.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Laſtly; whatever ſecond Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes they proceed from, or are rendred fit to be helpful and healthful by, that is no prejudice to the main Truth, that God makes them; nor derogates ought from the Glory that is due to him for the making of them, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we conſider them as ordinary Fountains for common uſe, or extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary for Health and Cure of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:153725:36"/>
            <head>SERMON II.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>REV. 14.7.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>— Worſhip him that made the Fountains of Waters.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>LED by the Authority of our Lord's Example, whoſe Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons moſtly were occaſional, preach'd upon viſible Texts, I ſingled out theſe Words, as not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuitable to this Aſſembly, the Centre of which are the adjoyning Wells.</p>
            <p>In the handling of them I reduced all I deſign'd to ſpeak, unto this eaſy Method. To inquire,</p>
            <p n="1">1. What is the ſole Object, ade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quate Reaſon, and right Notion of Religious Worſhip?</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:153725:37"/>2. Who made the Fountains, and in a ſhort Digreſſion how he made them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Why the Angel propounds him to be worſhip'd under that Notion, Maker of the Fountains; and how it may appear that this is a good and ſufficient Reaſon to oblige us to it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. To draw practical Inferences from the whole, proper to us at this Time and Place.</p>
            <p>The two former I have finiſh'd, and ſum'd up the philoſophick part of my Diſcourſe, of the Origine of Fountains, in ten Propoſitions: To which Diſcouſe my Subject almoſt neceſſitated me. For as it had been a fault to have affected it, and preſt and drag'd it in reluctantly, ſo had it been blame-worthy to have refus'd the Service it ſo freely and ſo fairly offered us, to aſſiſt us in our main Hypotheſis.</p>
            <p>'Twas an Obſervation worthy that great Mans Wiſdom who firſt made it, I mean the wiſe Lord <hi>Verulam.</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:153725:37"/> That a ſmattering in Philoſophy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes to Atheiſm, but a deeper ſearch into it, and knowledg of it, makes a good Divine, and a better Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>We have a common ſaying; <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi deſinit Philoſophus, ibi incipit Theologus:</hi> what Philoſophy begins, Divinity finiſheth. I ſhall therefore now pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to entertain you as becomes a Divine and Preacher, in anſwering the third inquiry, begging only thoſe Allowances which are but equal to be given to one, the obſcurity of whoſe Station can hardly avoid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting an habit of flat Expreſſion, and lower Notion.</p>
            <p>I haſte to the third and laſt Enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Why the Angel propounds him to be worſhip'd under this Notion, <hi>Maker of the Fountains?</hi> And how it may appear, that this is a good and ſufficient Reaſon, to oblige us to it?</p>
            <p>We may conceive a double Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of it.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:153725:38"/>1. To obviate the Superſtition and Idolatry of the World, which was uſed to worſhip the Fountains them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>All parts of the Creation were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus'd to Idolatry, eſpecially what ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd moſt glorious, and was found moſt beneficial: As the Heavens and their Hoſt, the Sun, Moon, and Stars for their Beauty and Influences, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Names of <hi>Jupiter, Apollo, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no, Diana,</hi> &amp;c. by the <hi>Romans;</hi> and of <hi>Baal,</hi> and <hi>Aſtaroth,</hi> &amp;c. by the Eaſtern Nations: ſo the Earth for its Fruitfulneſs, by the Name of <hi>Ceres</hi> and <hi>Tellus:</hi> And the Waters almoſt as much as any part of the World. The Sea for its vaſtneſs by the Name of <hi>Neptune,</hi> and the Rivers and Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, for the many benefits they yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for the perennity and conſtancy of their flowing, which ſeem'd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble an eternal being, and for the cool and ſhady places, in which they moſtly were, which ſtruck an aw, and repreſented ſome kind of Sacredneſs. Thus they had their <hi>Aquatick</hi> God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſs
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:153725:38"/> and Nymphs, their <hi>Naiades,</hi> which they ſuppoſed to dwell in them, or preſide over them.</p>
            <p>Now as 'twas uſual to obviate the worſhip of the Hoſt of Heaven, by directing to worſhip him that made the Heavens, and debaſing the Gods that made them not: <hi>The Gods which did not make the Heavens, ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd from under the Heavens,</hi> Jer. 10.11. Which Verſe was written in the <hi>Chaldee</hi> Tongue, that the <hi>Babylonians</hi> might underſtand it, tho all the reſt of the Book be written in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Language: So to convince them of the evil of worſhipping the Fountains, and divert them from it, he calls them to worſhip him that made them.</p>
            <p>And we may ſee the more evident need of it, if we conſider of how large a ſpread, this Superſtition was, and how deep root it had taken: for there being ſo many <hi>Miranda,</hi> and ſo great <hi>Beneficia;</hi> ſo many ſtupendous and unaccountable natural Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and ſo many Advantages ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruing
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:153725:39"/> to Men from Fountains of ſo various kinds: we need not be ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed at it, that they who worſhipped every thing, that was either very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, or very beneficial to their Life or Health, ſhould idolize them. And this continued ſo long, and the World was ſo pertinacious in it, that the Fathers of the Primitive Church, were forc'd to preach and write moſt inſtantly and ſeverely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it. To name but one. <hi>St. Aug. Serm. de Temp.</hi> 241. <hi>de Auguriis. Nec ad Arbores debent Chriſtiani vota reddere, nec ad Fontem orare, ſi ſe volunt per gratiam Dei de aeterno ſupplicio liberari;</hi> Chriſtians ought neither to pay Vows to Trees, nor pray at or to the Wells, if by the Grace of God they would be freed from Eternal Puniſhment. And a little after, <hi>Conteſtor vos coram Deo &amp; Angelis ejus ac de Nuncio, ut nec ad illa diabolica Convivia, quae aut ad fanum, ad Fonteſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> aut ad aliquas Arbores fiant, veniatis;</hi> I adjure ye before God and his Angels, that ye come not to thoſe Diabolical Feaſts
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:153725:39"/> which are made at Fountains and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Trees.</p>
            <p>And how many Superſtitions have been us'd almoſt, if not wholly to this very day, about Fountains, and the ſuppoſed tutelar Guardians of them, is not unknown to many, as might be inſtanced in the imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry St. <hi>Richard</hi> at the ſalt Wells in <hi>Worceſter-ſhire,</hi> and many others elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where.</p>
            <p>Now to obviate theſe evil Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſaith this preaching Angel, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip not the Wells or Fountains, or any ſuppoſed tutelary Deities, or Daemons reſiding in them, or preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding over them; but him that made them, and alone can bleſs them. I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolize not the likeneſs of any thing that is in the Waters under the Earth, nor the Virtues of thoſe Waters, nor the faint Reſemblance there ſeems to be of an eternal Being in their Peren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, nor any thing in them, or in any other Being which is made, but him that is the Maker of them, and the great Creator and Preſerver of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:153725:40"/> all things elſe; for <hi>nil factum adoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum,</hi> God made nothing to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipt'd, and nothing muſt be worſhip'd that is made.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But the ſecond, and more po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Reaſon why he directs us to worſhip him that made the Fountains, is, becauſe the making of them is a ſignal proof that he is the true God, and witneſs thoſe Perfections to be in him, for which he is truly adorable, and a meet Object, capable and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of Religious Adoration.</p>
            <p>I before ſuggeſted, that whatever Work of Nature or of Grace, mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſts the Author of it to be indued with infinite Perfections, or that he is a Being abſolutely and infinitely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, is a good and ſufficient Reaſon for the worſhipping of him.</p>
            <p>Now not to enquire into all, or more than the ſignal Trinity of Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, infinite Power, infinite Wiſdom, infinite Goodneſs; if the making of the Fountains be a valid and convincing Argument, that he who made them hath all theſe, is infinitely powerful,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:153725:40"/> wiſe and good, nay hath but any of them, (ſuppoſing that they might be parted) is perfect in Power only, or in Wiſdom, or in Goodneſs; that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone were a good Argument, both that he might and ought to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped.</p>
            <p>Not that the making of the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains proves no more: for I think it is eaſy to evince, that their Maker is an Eternal Being, from <hi>Prov.</hi> 8. and Eternal is truly an incommunicable Attribute, and a moſt adorable Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. And more might be named, but we may ſafely confine our ſelves to the three afore ſpecified; and if the making of them proves him to be all, or any of theſe, he muſt be worſhip'd that is ſuch, becauſe he is ſuch. I will touch them in order.</p>
            <p>Firſt; The making the Fountains proves him infinitely powerful, which we may conſider in ſeveral reſpects.</p>
            <p n="1">1. 'Tis a Work, and a Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Almighty Power, to produce out of nothing that which was not,<pb n="50" facs="tcp:153725:41"/> to give that a Being which had none before. Now <hi>there was a time when,</hi> or rather before time it ſelf was, <hi>there were no Fountains abounding with Water;</hi> Prov. 8.24. And his Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty <hi>Fiat</hi> gave them Being, who ſpake the Word, and they were made; who commanded and they were brought forth. By the Word of the Lord were the Waters made, and all the kinds and regions of them by the breath of his Mouth; and the firſt of <hi>Geneſis</hi> makes at leaſt as ſignal, and more repeated mention of the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, the Deep, the Seas, then of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth.</p>
            <p>Some think that the firſt matter, the Platoniſts ὕλη, the Scriptures <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hu</hi> and <hi>Bohu,</hi> which we call the <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os,</hi> was a watery fluid Maſs. Mr. <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net</hi>'s Theory of the Earth is chiefly built upon this Hypotheſis. And the great Abyſs, or <hi>Barathron,</hi> was the firſt or oldeſt of God's Works of Power; and the Iſſues and Outlets thereof, are the Effects of the ſame Power, and they are thoſe we call
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:153725:41"/> the Fountains of the great Deep: ſo that the making them, evidences him to be an Almighty Creator.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Having made and ſhut up thoſe vaſt Stores and Treaſuries of Water, 'tis a proof of his Power to unlock and unbar thoſe mighty Rocks and Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains which impriſoned and ſhut them in, and give them vent and paſſage, and open the very Womb of the Earth and Nature, that they may iſſue out. The Jews have a ſaying, that God keeps three Keys in his own Hand, the Key of the Womb, the Key of the Grave, and the Key of the Barn: ſinifying thereby, that Fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs or Barrenneſs, Life and Death, Plenty and Scarcity, depend imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately on him, and are great Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of his Power; and certainly it is no leſs to have the Key of the great Abyſs. 'Tis one of the moſt majeſtick Proofs of the Divine Power, which God himſelf inſiſts upon, <hi>Job</hi> 38.8, 11. <hi>To ſhut up the Sea with doors, and to ſay to it, Hither ſhalt thou go and no further, and here ſhall thy proud Wave
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:153725:42"/> ſtop themſelves.</hi> And 'tis no leſs Power which cleaves the mighty Rocks to let it out, than to bridle its ſwelling Surges, by the ſmalleſt Sand.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He makes new, ſudden extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Fountains when he pleaſes, without and beyond any natural ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent Cauſes ſtrikes the flinty Rock, and Waters guſh forth more readily than Sparks or Fire would by ſtrike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it with Steel. He muſt certainly be the Almighty Lord of Nature who can unhinge it, and change its Laws when ever he pleaſes, turning the dry Ground into Water-ſprings.</p>
            <p n="4">4. As the making Heaven and Earth prove his Omnipotence, for 'tis upon that account we profeſs in our Creed to believe him Almighty, <hi>I believe in God the Father Almighty, maker of Heaven and Earth,</hi> &amp;c. No leſs doth the making of the Sea and Fountains prove the ſame; for they are rank'd in the ſame Series in this very Text.</p>
            <p n="5">5. 'Tis a mighty proof of his Power to continue them, to ſupply
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:153725:42"/> and feed them for ſo many Ages, that they die not, but are juſtly ſtiled <hi>living Waters.</hi> Preſervation is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued Creation.</p>
            <p>Secondly; The making of the Fountains is a proof of his Wiſdom: as may appear,</p>
            <p n="1">1. In his contriving and building the whole Syſtem of univerſal Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſo admirably, ſo commodiouſly, every piece thereof agreeing ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently with all the others, that they are mutually ſubſervient. This har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monious Fabrick, this exact Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the whole, is a Work of that deep, that infinite and adorable Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: that it is an unanſwerable Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument for an intelligent Providence. And may put to ſhame and to ſilence all the Atheiſts, and Semi-Atheiſts in the World. And tho I confeſs 'tis more uſual to inſtance in the Heavens, as being more viſible, and to argue from the Scituation, Motion and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the Sun, Moon and Stars to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Earth, to render their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:153725:43"/> more propitious, that the whole may be fruitful, and a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious Habitation, that all may in good degree injoy their Comfort and their Bleſſing, and none be wholly depriv'd or deſtitute, nor ſcorch'd or ſpoiled by them. Yet with the like advantage might we argue from the Sea and Fountains; the ſpreading and diffuſing of which through ſo many hidden Veins within the Earth, and diſlodging themſelves in ſo many commodious places, and flowing in ſo many chryſtal, cooling, healthful Streams, both greatly beautifies and garniſheth the Earth, and renders it fertile and delightful for benefit of Man and Beaſts.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As they are ſo contrived, that all the <hi>Phaenomena</hi> about them, are unaccountable, and the wiſeſt and moſt inquiſitive Indigaters, are at a loſs, and cannot ſolve them, and find out the Reaſons of them: but muſt cry out in admiration of their Maker, <hi>his Wiſdom is unſearchable, and</hi> (in this, as much as in any Works of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:153725:43"/> Nature) <hi>paſt finding out.</hi> They muſt confeſs themſelves poſed, and ſay with <hi>David, Such Knowledg is too wonderful for me, 'tis high,</hi> 'tis deep, <hi>I cannot attain to it.</hi> Pſal. 139.6. And with the indefatigable <hi>Alſtedius,</hi> not be aſham'd to ſay, the beſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the Enquiries about them, is by that word of Modeſty, <hi>Neſcio,</hi> I cannot tell; and with the great Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher, dying, to <hi>Euripus, Non ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pio te,</hi> I cannot comprehend thee.</p>
            <p n="3">3. There appeareth great Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in cutting out their Chanels, ſpreading their Veins, proportioning their Depth, and Breadth, and Length, that they be not too rapid or too ſlow, that by a longer Tract they may be duly percolated, refin'd, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocted, imbued, and impregnated ſufficiently, and not exceſſively, with the virtues of the Mineral Soils, that make them uſeful. How wiſe is he who proportions all theſe, and an hundred more, in Number, Weight, and Meaſure?</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:153725:44"/>4. In the admirable and almoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite variety, and ſorts, and kinds of them. A Poet would call them, <hi>Luſus naturae laſcivientis,</hi> and tell you that wanton Nature never ſported it ſelf more gaily, then in the various ſorts and ſhapes of Springs and Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains; and in their ſtrange and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendous Properties; ſome ebbing and flowing as the Sea; ſome hot to ſeething, others as cold to freezing: ſome both, in every twenty four hours, hot in the Night, cold in the Day; ſome petrifying all that's put into them, others changing white the Hairs ſcattered on them, and of them who drink them: Some diute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, ſome purging; ſome molifying, other conſolidating; ſome ſalt, ſome ſweet; ſome acid, ſome inſipid; ſome limpid, others thick; ſome harſh, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſoft, ſmooth, oily, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In a word, the Sea hath not ſo many kinds of Fiſh, nor the Earth ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſorts of Beaſts, or Fruits, nor the Air ſuch diverſity of Fowls and Birds, as there are variety of Springs and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:153725:44"/> Fountains. <hi>O Lord, how manifold are theſe Works of thine! in Wiſdom haſt thou made them all; the Earth is full of thy Goodneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly; This, <hi>his Goodneſs,</hi> is the laſt of God's adorable Perfections, which bubbles up, yea flows exu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berantly upon us, in the Fountains which he makes. And if any be ſo ſenceleſs as to ask me, how the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the Fountains prove him to be good? It might be ſufficient to anſwer ſuch a Queſtion, by asking of another, <hi>viz.</hi> Art thou not aſham'd to ask it? or canſt thou move it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bluſhing?</p>
            <p>But to clear it; I mean by <hi>his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> his Beneficence, or doing Good. <hi>Thou art good, and doſt good,</hi> ſaith <hi>David</hi> unto God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.68. He therefore doth good becauſe he is good: But he is thereby known to be good, becauſe he doth good; and every Benefit he beſtows upon his Creatures, witneſs him to be a good God. <hi>Acts</hi> 14.17. how do the Wells
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:153725:45"/> and Fountains proclaim him to be ſo, as <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 93.3. of the <hi>Floods,</hi> we may ſay, <hi>The Springs, O Lord, have lifted up their Voice, the Springs lift up their Voice to ſhout forth the Goodneſs of their Maker, yea, they clap their Hands, (Pſal.</hi> 98.8.) applaudingly, to cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate his Praiſes.</p>
            <p>When grateful <hi>David</hi> had ſaid, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.5. <hi>The Earth is full of the Goodneſs of the Lord,</hi> he proves it, <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. becauſe <hi>he layeth up the Depth in Store-houſes,</hi> thereby to feed the Fountains. When <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſpeaking of the promis'd Land, ſaith to the Iſraelites, <hi>The Lord thy God bringeth thee into a good Land.</hi> The Character he gives of that Goodneſs, is, that 'twas <hi>a Land of Brooks of Water, of Fountains and Depths, that ſpring out of the Valleys and Hills.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And God is ſaid <hi>to open his good Treaſure,</hi> the Treaſures of his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.12. <hi>When he gives Rain from above,</hi> and ſo when he gives Fountains from beneath.</p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:153725:45"/>
            <p>Water is a great Mercy in the common uſe of it, the World could not continue or ſubſiſt without it; and unſpeakably ſweet and kind is that Clemency of God that makes and gives it. It is impoſſible to reckon up how many Benefits it yields us, or to declare how great that Godneſs is by which we do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy it; 'tis a Work fitter for our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, then our Reckoning; for Rhetorick than Arithmetick. And Spring-water is the beſt of Waters, the Life, the Spirits, the Quinteſſence of that beneficial Element, the moſt pure, pleaſant, wholſome, laſting, and every way moſt excellent and valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</p>
            <p>And becauſe ungrateful, we are more prone to make a right Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the worth of our Mercies, by their Wants, than their Injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, conſider how deplorable and ſad the want of Water is, and we ſhall ſoon know how good it is to have it; and thence learn to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg how good he is that gives it.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:153725:46"/> But if common Waters be ſo great a Bleſſing, then extraordinary Springs are no common Mercies. And God is to be confeſſed very good for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſuch mollifying Baths, God's own <hi>Betheſdahs</hi> and <hi>Siloam</hi>-pools; which ſeem attended conſtantly with ſome good Angel, and not only viſited at rare and ſeldom Seaſons. Purging-Springs, abſtirging Wells, opening Obſtructions, ſweetning the Blood, thinning tough viſcous Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, preventing ſome, and grapling with and conquering other moſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate and chronical Diſtempers, which were <hi>opprobria Medicorrm,</hi> ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fled the beſt experienced, the eldeſt, the firſt-born Sons of <hi>Apollo</hi> and <hi>Aeſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapius:</hi> which <hi>Leviathan</hi>-like, eſteem'd the choiceſt Recipes, the keeneſt Shafts of <hi>Galen</hi> or <hi>Hippocrates, Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celſus</hi> or <hi>Vanhelmont,</hi> but as Straw or rotten Wood. Such are theſe Wells, God hath inrich'd this barren Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try with, which we come hither to make uſe of, and to wait upon his Providence in the uſing of them.
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:153725:46"/> How exuberantly doth God's Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs flow in theſe? O that with be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming Gratitude, and Love we could with a ſpiritual Guſt reliſh and taſte it in every Glaſs we drink! Theſe are his Laboratories, who ſtiles himſelf <hi>Jehova Rophi,</hi> Exod. 15.26. <hi>I am the Lord that healeth thee;</hi> and whom <hi>David (Pſal.</hi> 103.3.) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts us to bleſs <hi>for healing all our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes.</hi> Theſe are Alimbecks, where Almighty Goodneſs draws the Tinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and the Extracts, prepares the Spirits, makes the Infuſion, mixes the healthful Potions. And how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemly is it to open our Lips to drink them in, and not to open them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, to confeſs his Goodneſs, and give out due Praiſes unto him that made them!</p>
            <p n="3">3. His <hi>Goodneſs</hi> appears in diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering the Vertues of ſuch Waters. How many uſeful things are loſt for want of being known? Divine Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency is ſeldom ſingle, content with one Act; 'twas one Mercy to make them what they are; a ſecond to let
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:153725:47"/> us know what he had made them; and thirdly, to vouchſafe us Liberty and Opportunity to uſe them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. 'Tis great <hi>Goodneſs</hi> in God to make them uſeful and beneficial, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the common or the mineral Springs. Man lives not by Bread on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but by the Word which proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out of God's Mouth. Dead things cannot miniſter to our Lives, but by the bleſſing of the living God; neither can Phyſick prepar'd by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or by Art, heal or help us with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the concurrent Influence of him, who immediately makes one, and muſt as immediately bleſs both.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Laſtly; Let me add one fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Manifeſtation of his <hi>Goodneſs</hi> in making the Fountains, which may ſenſibly affect thoſe who are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd, how little ſoever it may ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify to others. <hi>David</hi> juſtly aſcribes it to the Goodneſs of God to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for the Poor; <hi>Thou, Lord, haſt of thy Goodneſs provided for the Poor.</hi> How many poor Families doth God provide for by the Wells! They are
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:153725:47"/> truly Silver Streams, they feed the Hungry, and cloath the Naked, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich the Country, yield a plentiful Crop, and large Harveſt to them who neither plow nor ſow. <hi>O that Men would praiſe the Lord for this Goodneſs, and for his wonderful Works to the Children of Men!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus have I ſhew'd you why we are moſt juſtly call'd upon to worſhip him that made the Fountains of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: Becauſe in his making of them, there is a glorious diſcovery of many adorable Perfections, and amongſt the reſt, his Almighty Power, his unſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Wiſdom, and his inexhauſtible Goodneſs. All which not only allow and give leave, but oblige and give good reaſon, why we ſhould worſhip him with all the Zeal and Love and Fervor that we can.</p>
            <p>Which Conſideration leads me to the fourth and laſt thing propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the beginning of this Diſcourſe, that is, To draw practical Inferences from the whole, and make Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:153725:48"/> of it, proper to us at this Place and Time.</p>
            <p>If we muſt worſhip him that made the Fountains, that is, honour, love, fear, ſerve him, pray to him, and give him Thanks, becauſe he made them, and diſcovers ſo many adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Perfections to be in him by his making of them: Then let us briefly inquire, <list>
                  <item>1. What Prohibitions.</item>
                  <item>2. What poſitive Duties flow from hence.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>God's Word is a two-edged Sword, <hi>utrinque acutus,</hi> it cuts on both ſides. When it injoyns a Duty, it prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits what is contrary; and when it prohibits Sin, it injoyns the Good, which is contrary to the Evil it for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids.</p>
            <p>If therefore we muſt worſhip him that made the Fountains: Then, <list>
                  <item>1. We muſt not neglect him.</item>
                  <item>2. Not do any thing that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his Worſhip.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:153725:48"/>1. Let us not neglect, forget, or leave out him that made them, gave them their Virtues, and muſt bleſs them, if they do us good. Let us not drink as the Beaſts of the Earth, which all the while they drink, look only down upon the Waters they are drinking of; but as the Birds of Heaven, which ſip and look upward. When we drink we lift up our Heads, 'tis a neceſſary Poſture: make a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of this neceſſity; and when you lift up your Heads in drinking, lift up your Eyes, your Hearts to God, in ſome devout Ejaculations, in ſome ſpiritual Hallelujahs.</p>
            <p>Good Lord vouchſafe to bleſs theſe Waters both to me, and to all that drink them; O thou that madeſt the Fountains, give me cauſe, and give me an Heart to praiſe thee for the making of them. <hi>O ye Wells, bleſs ye the Lord, praiſe him, and magnify him for ever! who forgiveth all thy Sins, and healeth all thy Diſeaſes.</hi> Glory be to thee, O God, whoſe Power, Wiſdom, Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs theſe Wells proclaim; thou ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:153725:49"/> them their Virtues, thou conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueſt their flowing, thou haſt made them helpful to me and many others; O continue forth thy Loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to us, and grant us all thy Grace to ſpend the Health we wait up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee for, in the Service of the Giver.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly; If we muſt worſhip him that made theſe Fountains, then let us do nothing that's contrary to it, or miſbecoming thoſe that worſhip him.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In general: Provoke him not in any kind to Jealouſy, leſt they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as the Waters of Jealouſy to the the guilty Woman, <hi>Numb.</hi> 5.27. a Curſe, <hi>and cauſe the Belly to ſwell, and Thigh to rot.</hi> God hath us here at our Good-behaviour. 'Twas no ſmall Aggravation of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> Sin, that they <hi>provoked God at the Sea, even at the red Sea,</hi> Pſal. 106.7. where he ſignaliz'd his Mercy, <hi>by the Waters covering their Enemies, that there was not any of them left,</hi> verſ. 11. Your Diſtempers are your Enemies;
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:153725:49"/> if you expect to have them drown'd, or waſh'd away, provoke him not at the Wells, even at <hi>Tunbridg-Wells,</hi> where you expect his Help for your Cure; render them not as the Waters of <hi>Meribah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am neither of ſo ſtoical a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, moroſe Humour, or affected Converſation, as to cenſure other Mens Liberties, or to refuſe to take my part in innocent Divertiſements, and healthful Recreations. Take your Pleaſures in God's Name. But love not your Pleaſures more than God: neither let your Pleaſures be ungodly, nor the purſuit of your Bodies Health run you into Souls Sickneſs. Be merry, but withal be wiſe. Divert your ſelves, but turn not out of God's way: uſe your Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, but abuſe them not, uſe them not unlawfully: Provide for your Satisfaction; always provided, you make not Proviſion for the Fleſh to fulfil its Luſts.</p>
            <p>In a word, ſo walk, ſo bowl, ſo dance, ſo play, that you ſtake not
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:153725:50"/> your Souls, nor by any of theſe, or other Paſtimes, rob your ſelves of time to pray to, or to praiſe that God, <hi>who made thoſe Wells,</hi> which are the Centre of this great Confluence: or may render you aſham'd, afraid, or otherwiſe unfit, to bow your Knees, or lift up your Faces, Hands or Hearts unto his holy Habitation; and that neither the Foams of impure Luſts, nor the Froth of leſs criminal Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, may pollute or damp the Altar, nor render unſavoury the Incenſe of your Evening Sacrifice. <hi>Tertullian</hi> hath left a brave and noble Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of the Primitive Chriſtians, worthy our Imitation, yea our Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition. <hi>That they ſo ate, ſo drank, ſo traded, ſo converſed in the day, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came thoſe who remembred that they were to pray ere they ſlept at Night.</hi> O that I could always do ſo. And I can wiſh you nothing better, tho I love you as my ſelf.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, and more particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Look upon theſe Wells as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated and made ſacred by an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:153725:50"/> Preſence of the God of Nature, in and with them; and by the helpful Virtues, and healing Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, that he that makes the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, hath endu'd them with. And ſo <hi>procul procul eſto prophani.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After the Command which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyns God's Worſhip, follows that which ſo ſeverely forbids the taking of his Name in vain. What doth this ſignify leſs, then that in vain we worſhip him, if we ceaſe not to take his Name in vain?</p>
            <p>I beſeech you therefore give me leave, with that Zeal which becomes my Sacerdotal Character, and yet with that Modeſty, which knows my own meaneſs in that Sacred Order, to beſeech you to be tender of the Honour of the Name of God.</p>
            <p>I hope I underſtand the difference betwixt reproving and reproaching; and tho we are allowed and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to reprove ſome Sinners ſharply, cuttingly, as the Greek Word ſignifies, yet to add reproachful Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections to needful Reproofs, would
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:153725:51"/> be as if a Chirurgion ſhould inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nom the point of his Lancet, or Edge of his Inciſion-knife; and thereby add a throbbing Anguiſh, a vexing Torment, and deadly Inflammation, to the unavoidable, but ſafe and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial ſmart, to which the Patient would be perſwaded to ſubmit with Willingneſs, in hope of Cure.</p>
            <p>I can ſincerely ſay, I honour your Perſons, and love your Souls, and would not diſpleaſe you, leſt I there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by hinder your profiting by my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaties or Advice.</p>
            <p>I beſeech you therefore, yea I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain and again beſeech you, let not the moſt guilty, the moſt criminal Offender think himſelf reproach'd, while I reprove the Sin of common Swearing, the too frequent noiſe of which, greatly abates the innocent Pleaſures of this Place and Seaſon. 'Tis the direct <hi>Antitheſis</hi> to the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip we are required to give Him that made the Fountains; 'tis a caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing off his Fear, 'tis a trampling his Glory under foot; 'tis a rendring his
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:153725:51"/> great, his holy, his adorable Name, vile and contemptible, cheap and baſe, a low, a common thing.</p>
            <p>I hope I may without Offence profeſs, that I cannot but pitty the Errors of their Education, who e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem it a piece of good Breeding to blaſpheme the Name of God, and account it the moſt ornamental and graceful Accompliſhment of their Language, with a graceleſs Fool-har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs to dare him to his Face to damn them. If you believe there is a God, (and who hath the Patience to be eſteem'd an Atheiſt?) and that he is a God indeed, a Being abſolutely perfect, infinitely great and good, omniſcient, holy, juſt and true, you may take his word, <hi>He will not hold him guiltleſs that takes his Name in vain.</hi> And I aſſure you 'tis much wiſer and ſafer to believe in time, then to find to Eternity, how fearful a thing it is to fall into the Hands of the everlaſting God.</p>
            <p>As for my ſelf, (and I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in this, I ſpeak the joint Senſe
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:153725:52"/> of my Brethren in the ſame ſacred Order) I ſpeak it freely: He deſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates his Sacerdotal Character, and is unworthy to be a Prieſt in our holy Church, who is ſo unfaithful and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, as not to mind them of their Failings, who in this kind ſin through Inadvertency and Weakneſs, or ſo cowardly, as through want of Zeal for God, and love to his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, dares not admoniſh them, who thus ſin in an affected Contempt of God and Religion. It was the cuſtom of the Jews, to rend their Garments when they heard the Name of the holy bleſſed God blaſphemed. And for us of the Clergy, we deſerve no pity, if it rend not our Hearts to hear the ſacred Name of God ſo vilely rent in pieces, tho our Gowns were rent from off our Backs.</p>
            <p>But I haſten to the poſitive Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If we muſt worſhip Him that made the Fountains: Then by parity of Reaſon, let us learn to inforce up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our ſelves, a due, an awful Senſe
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:153725:52"/> of God: from every Creature, in the making of which he hath mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted forth his glorious, his adorable Perfections; God's Name is written on them all; <hi>Praeſentem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Deum quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libet herba refert.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Univerſe is a great Volume, and every Creature is a Letter in it; as in their orderly Conjunction, you may ſpell and read his adorable Excellencies compleatly and at large, ſo every ſingle Letter hath its Signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and Sound. But as in the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phabet, ſome are Vowels, ſound ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and give a ſound to others: ſo in the Book of Nature, ſome of God's Works are Vowels, very vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal; ſuch as the Heaven, the Earth, the Sea and the Fountains; worſhip him, love and admire him in the leaſt: for God is <hi>Magnus in minimis,</hi> great in the leaſt that he hath made: <hi>Digitus Dei</hi> may be ſeen in them. But,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Worſhip him more ſignally for making the Fountains. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.1. <hi>David</hi> ſtirs up himſelf, <hi>Bleſs the Lord
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:153725:53"/> O my Soul:</hi> and then he gives the Reaſons why, and a principal one is laid down <hi>Verſ.</hi> 10. <hi>Becauſe he ſends the Springs into the Valleys,</hi> Pſal. 95. which the Church hath wiſely cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen as a Preface to our Publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip every Morning, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 1. <hi>O come let us ſing unto the Lord, let us heartily rejoice in the Strength of our Salvation;</hi> Verſ. 4. <hi>Becauſe in his Hands are the deep places of the Earth;</hi> Verſ. 5. <hi>The Sea is his, and he made it,</hi> and the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of it. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 6. <hi>O come, let us therefore worſhip and fall down before his Foot-ſtool.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Then him that made the extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Fountains for Medicine, for Health: ſhall ſo much Power, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Goodneſs ſhine forth in them, and we be blind and not obſerve them? or dumb, and not expreſs a deep and grateful ſenſe of them? O that a bleſſed God would ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>add one healing Vertue more unto them, a Power to cure the Indevoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our too little thankful Hearts! Shall they be counted worthy ſo great
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:153725:53"/> Expence, of Travel, Time and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and not be worthy our thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Praiſes, Love and Service? O thou that madeſt theſe Wells, and haſt opened the flinty Rocks, ſo that Streams have iſſued out, open our ſtony Hearts, that ſweeteſt Streams of Love, of Praiſe and Adoration, may flow from thence, and never be dried up!</p>
            <p n="4">4. If he muſt be worſhip'd that made the Fountains in the Fields and Deſarts, how much more he that made thoſe in the Garden, in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe of God, I mean his Church. We call that ſacred Veſſel, where the Covenant of Chriſtianity was ſeal'd 'twixt God and us, <hi>the Font.</hi> He makes the other as the God of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; but the Fountain of our Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm is ſignally made by him, as the God of Grace. 'Twas he that ſent St. <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> to baptize with Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>John</hi> 1.33.</p>
            <p>And his bleſſed Son, the <hi>holy Jeſus,</hi> after he was riſen from the Dead, and entred into his ſtate of Exaltation,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:153725:54"/> gave Commiſſion and Command to his Diſciples to <hi>baptize all Nations in the Name of the Father, Son, and Holy-Ghost.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Baptiſm is a moſt ſolemn Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Act of Worſhip, and Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Acts are ingaging Acts. 'Tis as the boaring of our Ear at the door<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſt of God's Houſe, to ſhew that we muſt ſerve him for ever. We therein receive the mark of the Lamb of God on our Fore-heads, and on our Right-hands; 'tis the very Badg and Cognizance of the Worſhippers of the true God, through Jeſus Chriſt, by the Holy Ghoſt, in all whoſe Names we receive it, and to whoſe Service we are conſecrated by it: we thereby oblige our ſelves to his Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip both in the largeſt and ſtricteſt Notions, to his entire Service in univerſal unreſerved Obedience, and all inward and external Acts of Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, both in Soul and Body. And by how much the Privileges of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm are more and greater, and the Obligations of it ſtronger and more
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:153725:54"/> indiſpenſable; ſo much more zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly ſhould we worſhip him that made it for us, and hath admitted us unto it.</p>
            <p>Few Aggravations inhance and heighten the guilt and provocation of our Sins ſo much, as that they are the Sins of baptized ones: this dyes them of a deeper Purple than thoſe of <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Sidon, Sodom</hi> and <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe mineral Waters may, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things put to them, loſe both their Taſte and Virtue, in the Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt Phraſe be <hi>precipitated,</hi> that tho they are drunk, they neither heal nor help. Every deliberate and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Sin deſecrates the Waters, which were conſecrated to the myſtical waſhing away of Sin: Precipitates baptiſmal Waters, that their Virtue ſubſides and ſinks, to the bottom of the Font, that tho they ſtill may wet, they will not waſh; though they may be ſprinkled, they will not cleanſe.</p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:153725:55"/>
            <p>How unpardonable an Affront would it be to this honourable Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, if any ſhould be ſo impudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rude or wicked, as to pollute or poiſon theſe Wells we come to drink of? What is it then to abuſe that Blood of ſprinkling, by which we were ſanctified, and to do deſpite to that Spirit of Grace which over-ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows theſe ſacred Waters?</p>
            <p>An involuntary innocent ſtaining of the Font, hath branded an impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Name in all ſucceeding Ages, <hi>Leo Coproninus.</hi> The caſting of a dead Dog into a Well, which was the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſupply for the Garriſon which kept it, loſt one of the ſtrongeſt and moſt impregnable Forts, <hi>Stetguard.</hi> Our voluntary ſinning after and againſt our Baptiſm, poiſons the very Font, caſts a dead Dog into the Well of Grace, nay, is an actual ſurrender in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Hands whom we have renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and ſhould ſtand in defiance of for ever.</p>
            <p>I beſeech you, I adjure you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, worſhip that God which made
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:153725:55"/> the Font of your Baptiſm, by a ſound believing of the good Promiſes he made to you, and making good the Promiſes you there made to him: for as there is no greater cauſe of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay of Chriſtian Piety, than the not underſtanding or forgetting our Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmal Covenant, and the indiſpenſable Obligation it brings us under, to Faith, Repentance, and unreſerved new O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience; ſo there is no Remedy more likely to retrieve its Honour, and to reſtore the power of it in the World, than a daily ſerious remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring of it, and hearty deſire and ſtudy to live up to it.</p>
            <p n="5">5. If we muſt worſhip him, love, ſerve, adore him that made the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, and made the Font; how much more him that made the Source and Spring of that very Fountain, that <hi>Fountain opened for Sin and for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs,</hi> Zech. 13.1. the Blood, the Spirit of Chriſt?</p>
            <p>When <hi>Longinus,</hi> as Tradition names him, with that accurſed Spear pierced the Side and Heart of our
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:153725:56"/> moſt bleſſed Lord, yet hanging on that more accurſed Tree, forthwith there came out Blood and Water; <hi>John</hi> 19.34. The Church hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways reckon'd theſe the vital Springs of the Health-giving Sacraments. Chriſt calls himſelf <hi>the living Water, John</hi> 4. and he calls the Spirit by the ſame Name, <hi>John</hi> 7.38, 39. <hi>He that believes in me, out of his Belly ſhall flow Rivers of living Water; this ſpake he of the Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And 'tis agreeable to his Father's Language, Pſal. 44.3. <hi>I will pour Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter upon him that is thirſty, and Floods upon the dry Ground. I will pour my Spirit upon thy Seed,</hi> Iſa. 44.3.</p>
            <p>If the love of God in giving his Son be ſet forth ſo emphatically with an ἑςτως, <hi>God ſo loved the World that he gave his only begotten Son,</hi> ſo freely, ſo fully, ſo inconceivably, as no Tongue can expreſs, as no Heart can conceive; with what Fervours of Love and Thankfulneſs ſhould we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it and return it?</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:153725:56"/>6. Worſhip him that is not only the Maker of the Fountains, but the very Fountain of all things; ὁ ῶν, <hi>the Fountain of living Waters:</hi> Jer. 2.13. The Fountain of our Being, <hi>in whom we live, and move, and have our Being;</hi> and for whom, as well as by whom, we were all made. God made us all to worſhip himſelf: for he made the World to manifeſt his Glory, that he might be known to be, and to be ſuch as indeed he is, and have the Glory of being ſuch; and to give him that Glory (which is peculiar to intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Natures) is properly to worſhip him.</p>
            <p>And the Fountain of all our Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral, Spiritual, and Eternal Mercies preſent, future, all we have, and all we hope for.</p>
            <p>Nay, the Fountain of the very Deity, as the Schools call God the Father, <hi>Fontem Dietatis,</hi> who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municates the Divine Nature to the Son and Holy Ghoſt, as Light and Heat flow from the Body of the Sun, tho they abide in it, and be one with it.</p>
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:153725:57"/>
            <p>Laſtly; If all muſt worſhip him that made the Fountains; Then they eſpecially who have built him an Houſe for his Worſhip at theſe famous Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains: And it will be little better then a mocking of him, to erect him an Houſe for his Worſhip, and to neglect that Worſhip for which it was erected.</p>
            <p>And tho I am very far from im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing Laws, or preſcribing Rules to this Honourable Aſſembly; yet give me leave with that modeſt freedom which becomes my Office, to remind you of ſomewhat at leaſt very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemly; and which I charitably hope, proceeds ſolely or chiefly from want of Conſideration.</p>
            <p>You exactly underſtand all the Punctilio's of Honour, all the Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of what is Decent, Juſt and Fit. Let me therefore appeal to you what Reſpect, what Deference is due to God, who is, and calls himſelf a Great King. How comely it would be, (or rather how uncomely 'tis to do the contrary) not to continue
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:153725:57"/> your Gaming upon the very ſpot, in time of Publick Prayer. I beſeech you, if you will not joyn with us in our ſolemn Worſhip, yet modeſtly forbear to affront it, and Him to whom we pay it.</p>
            <p>Give me leave to conclude with one more humble Motion. 'Tis an expreſs Branch of Divine Worſhip to build God an Houſe, 'twill be no leſs to indow it now 'tis built. An eaſy Liberality from New comers, who find a Chappel ready prepar'd by our Charge and Care, (not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding the pious Charity of thoſe who have already given to its buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding) may ſettle a decent Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for an Able Miniſter, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly to offioiate in it, and preach to the Neighbouring Inhabitants all the Year.</p>
            <p>'Tis a certainly deſolate place in the depth of Winter, ſtill, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the many fair Houſes which are lately built. And the badneſs of the Ways, and diſtance of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, I fear, occaſions in many, too
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:153725:58"/> great a neglect of God's Worſhip, and their own Souls. Had they an Able Miniſter to reſide conſtantly among them, the Wo of dwelling in this <hi>Meſech</hi> would be much abated, and theſe Deſerts would become a <hi>Mount Sion,</hi> and theſe Tents of <hi>Ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar</hi> like the Curtains of <hi>Solomon,</hi> an Emblem of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We of the Clergy, who come hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for preſervation, or recovery of Health, give you our Labors freely, tho we have no cauſe to be aſham'd of what we gave to the Erection of the Place we labour in. And you may the better bear with us, while in the behalf of them that ſerve us here, we plead with you to leave a Bleſſing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind you, That as God hath endow'd theſe Wells with laſting Streams and Virtues, you would endow this Houſe built to his Name ſo near them, that the Waters of the Sanctuary may flow from hence, with a conſtant Perennity, like to the Waters of theſe Wells, and with an Healthfulneſs to the Souls of thoſe that dwell here,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:153725:58"/> which may equal, or exceed the Uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of the Waters to the Bodies of us Strangers, who come hither to drink them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And now, Oh thou most glorious Lord, who hast made the Fountains of Waters, and thereby manifeſted forth thy Almighty Power, thy unſearchable Wiſdom, and inexhauſtible Goodneſs, which render thee a moſt ſutable Object of all poſſible Adoration, Love and Service; Accept we beſeech thee, the Sacrifice of Thanksgiving and Praiſe, which we offer to thee from the Altar of an humble Heart, for making of theſe Fountains, and making known and continuing their uſeful Virtues, and for bleſſing them to any of us. And we further bleſs thy glorious Name, who art the Fountain of Living Waters, and in whom are all our Springs, for all the Streams of Mercy that flow from thee, eſpecially for thy Son, and thy Spirit, thy Word, and thy Sacraments, and that ſutable Portion of it we have now been made partakers of: Beſeeching thee ſo
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:153725:59"/> to write in our Hearts by the Finger of thy Spirit, what we have heard with our outward Ears, that it may bring forth in us the Fruit of good Living, to the Glory of thy holy Name, the good Example of our fellow Chriſtians, the preſent Comfort, and the eternal Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our precious Souls, through Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our deareſt Lord: To whom with thy Majeſty, and eternal Spirit, be rendred, as is most due, all Honour, Love, Thanksgiving, Praiſe and Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, now and for evermore.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="meditations">
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:153725:59"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Devout Meditations of Cardinal</hi> Bellarmine, <hi>made Engliſh.</hi> Of the Conſideration of the Waters, and chiefly of Fountains,</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>THE Water holds the ſecond place amongſt the Elements of this World: and if that be rightly look'd upon, a ſtep may be made of it to aſſiſt the Heart's Aſcent to God. And if we will premiſe a general Conſideration of Water, then draw out of the Fountains a ſpecial Aſcent to God.</p>
               <p>Water is moiſt and cold, and from hence it hath theſe five Properties: For, 1. It waſheth and cleanſeth
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:153725:60"/> away Spots and Defilements. 2. It quencheth Fire. 3. It cools and ſlakes the heat of Thirſt. 4. It joyns into one many and different things. Laſtly; So low as it deſcends, ſo high it will aſcend again: All which are manifeſt Symbols and Foot-ſteps of that God who is the maker of all things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Water waſheth off bodily Stains: God waſheth off thoſe that are ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual. <hi>Thou ſhalt waſh me,</hi> ſaith <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, and I ſhall be whiter than Snow; Pſal.</hi> 51.7. For altho Contrition, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, Prieſts, Alms-deeds, do waſh away Sins, which are the Stains of the Heart: All theſe are but In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments and Diſpoſitions. He that is the Author of this waſhing, is God alone. <hi>I even I am he that blotteth out thy Tranſgreſſions, for mine own ſake,</hi> ſaith God by <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> Chap. 43.25. And therefore the Phariſees mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring againſt Chriſt, ſaid, <hi>Who can forgive Sins but God only?</hi> Luke 7. 49. And they were not miſtaken in aſcribing unto God only, the ſupream
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:153725:60"/> Power of forgiving Sins: But in that that they believ'd not Chriſt to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> God, and ſo blaſphem'd, and ſpake Truth in the ſame breath.</p>
               <p>Neither doth God only, like Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, waſh away Spots, but will alſo be called by the Name of Water; <hi>John</hi> 7.38. <hi>He that believeth on me, as the Scripture hath ſaid, out of his Belly ſhall flow Rivers of living Water. But this ſpake he of the Spirit which they that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve on him ſhould receive: for the Holy Ghoſt was not yet given, becauſe Jeſus was not yet glorified.</hi> Therefore the holy Spirit, which is very God, is living Water. And of this Water ſpeaks <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> Chap. 36.25. <hi>I will ſprinkle clean Water upon you, and ye ſhall be clean from all your Filthineſs, and from your Idols will I cleanſe you.</hi> And becauſe this celeſtial and uncrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Water far excels the Virtues of this terreſtrial and created Water, we will take notice of three Differences betwixt the waſhing of created and uncreated Water.</p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:153725:61"/>
               <p>Firſt; That which is created, waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Bodies Spots, but not all, for many it cannot get out unleſs it be help'd by Soap and other Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: but uncreated Water waſheth out throughly all kind of Spots: for in the fore-cited place 'tis ſaid, <hi>You ſhall be clean from all your Filthineſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly; Created Water rarely waſheth Spots ſo clean away, as to leave no Marks or Shadows of them: But uncreated Water waſheth ſo, that what is waſhed with it, is whiter and fairer then it was before it was defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. <hi>Thou ſhalt waſh me,</hi> ſaith <hi>David, and I ſhall be whiter than Snow.</hi> And the Lord himſelf ſaith by <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> Chap. 1.18. <hi>Tho your Sins be as Scarlet, they ſhall be as white as Snow: tho they be red like Crimſon, they ſhall be as Wooll.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly; Created Water waſheth away natural Spots, which reſiſt not him that waſheth them: But un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>created Water waſheth away volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Spots, which cannot be rinſed off, unleſs the Soul be willing, and ſpontaneouſly conſent to him that
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:153725:61"/> rinſeth it. But ſo great and admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble is the Virtue of this Water, that it ſweetly penetrates hearts of Stone, and is reſiſted by no hard Heart, becauſe it makes it not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, as St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> rightly obſerves, <hi>Lib. de Praed. SS. cap.</hi> 8.</p>
               <p>Who can underſtand, O Lord, with how admirable Methods thou breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Faith into the Hearts of the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers, and poureſt Humility in-the Heats of the proud, and inſtilleſt Love into the Hearts of thy Enemies, that he who a little before breathing Threatnings and Slaughter, did per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute thee in thy Diſciples, being ſuddenly chang'd, did willingly bear the Threats and Violences of the Perſecutors for thee, and for thy Church! It is too much for me to ſearch into thy Secrets, and I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther know the efficacy of thy Grace by ſweet Experience, than by ſearch: and becauſe I know this Water of thine, to be a voluntary Shower, deſign'd for thine own Heritage, as thy Prophet ſingS, therefore I moſt
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:153725:62"/> humbly and ſubmiſsly beg, that I may be found in thine Inheritance, and it may pleaſe thy Grace to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend into the Earth of my Heart, that it continue not towards thee like Earth without Water, dry and barren, as 'tis of it ſelf, being not ſufficient ſo much as to think the leaſt that's good. But let's us proceed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <p>VVAter quencheth Fire, and that heavenly Water, <hi>viz.</hi> the Grace of the holy Spirit, in an admirable way and manner, quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Fire of carnal Luſts. 'Tis true, Faſtings and corporal Mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations do much avail to quench this Burning, but provided they be uſed as Inſtruments of the Grace of the Holy Ghoſt, otherwiſe of themſelves alone they ſignifie but very little: For Love is the principal of the Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Paſſions of the Mind, that governs them all, and all obey it; Love will not be forc'd, and if it be
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:153725:62"/> ſtopt of one ſide, it will find Paſſage in another; Love fears nothing, dares all things, conquereth all things, thinks nothing hard or impoſſible to it ſelf. Laſtly; a leſſer Love will yield to none, but to that Love that's greater and more mighty: ſo carnal Love, whether it purſue the Riches or Delights of the World, will only yield unto the Love of God. As ſoon as the Water of the holy Spirit begins to drop into the Heart of any Man, forthwith carnal Love begins to wax cold. Bleſſed <hi>Auguſtine</hi> may be our Witneſs, who being accuſtomed to indulge his Luſt, and held it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for him to live without a Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male Conſort, yet when he began to taſte the Grace of the holy Spirit, cry'd out in the ninth Book of his Confeſſions, <hi>How ſweet did it preſently become to me, to want the Suavities of Trifles, and the loſs of thoſe that were my greateſt Fear, now was my Joy to be rid off: for thou didſt caſt them out, who art thy ſelf the true and higheſt Sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; thou didſt caſt them out, and didſt
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:153725:63"/> thy ſelf enter in their ſtead, who art ſweeter than all Pleaſure, but not to Fleſh and Blood; brighter than all Light, but more inward than any Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret; higher than all Honour, but not to the high-minded.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <p>FUrther; Water ſlakes the Thirſt, and nothing but this heavenly Water can put an end to the various, moſt troubleſome, and almoſt infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite deſires of the Hearts of Men. So Truth it ſelf, ſpeaking to the <hi>Samaritan</hi> Woman, hath taught us, <hi>John</hi> 4.13. <hi>Whoſoever drinketh of this Water, ſhall thirſt again; but whoſoever ſhall drink of the Water that I ſhall give him, ſhall never thirſt.</hi> And the caſe is plainly this, <hi>The Eye is not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with ſeeing, nor the Ear filled with hearing.</hi> Eccleſ. 1.8. What ever can be offered to a Man, cannot ſatiate his deſire, ſeeing he is capable of infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Good, and all created things are finite: but he that begins to drink
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:153725:63"/> of celeſtial Water, in which are comprehended all things, deſires no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, ſeeks for nothing more.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <p>WAter conjoyns and brings into one the things that ſeem impoſſible to be united: So many Grains of Bread-Corn, by mixture of Water, are made one Loaf; and of many Particles of Earth, by adding Water to them, Bricks are made: but much more eaſily and indiſſolubly the Water of the holy Spirit cauſeth many Men to become one Heart and one Soul; as is ſpoken in the <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles,</hi> Chap. 4.22. of the firſt Chriſtians, on whom the Holy Ghoſt had immediately before deſcended. And our Lord, when going to his Father, both commended and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told this Unity, which the Water of the holy Spirit maketh, when he ſaith, <hi>John</hi> 17.20. <hi>Neither pray I for theſe alone, but for them alſo that ſhall believe on me through their Word, that they
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:153725:64"/> all may be one, as thou Father art in me, and I in thee, that they alſo may be one in us.</hi> And a little after, <hi>that they may be one, even as we are one, I in them and thou in me, that they may be made perfect in one.</hi> To which Unity alſo the Apoſtle exhorts in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> Chap. 4.3. <hi>Endeavouring to keep the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Spirit in the Bond of Peace. There is one Body, and one Spirit, even as ye are called in one hope of your Calling.</hi> O happy Union! which makes many Men to be one Body of Chriſt, which is govern'd by one Head, and eats of one Bread, and drinks of one Cup, and lives of one Spirit, and cleaving to God, is made one Spirit with him. What can a Servant more deſire, than that he ſhould not only be made partaker of all his Lord's Goods, but alſo by the indiſſoluble Bond of Love, be made one with him, his almighty and moſt wiſe, and moſt beautiful Lord? But all this does the Grace of the holy Spirit effect, as living and enlivening
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:153725:64"/> Water, when it is devoutly received in the Heart, and preſerv'd with all Diligence, and ſollicitous Care.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <p>LAſtly; Water aſcends ſo high as it deſcends from above; and becauſe the holy Spirit comes down from the higheſt Heaven, upon Earth, therefore in that Man in whoſe Heart he is receiv'd, he becomes <hi>a Fountain of Water ſpringing up into Eternal Life,</hi> as our Lord ſpeaks to the Woman of <hi>Samaria;</hi> that is to ſay, a Man born again of Water and the holy Spirit, and hath the ſame Spirit dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in his Heart, lifts up thither the Fruits of his Grace from whence that Grace deſcended: therefore, O my Soul, being taught and excited by theſe Words of Scripture, ſay to thy Father, again and again, with groan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings that cannot be utter'd, Give me this Water which may ſcour off all my Spots, which may quench the heat of Concupiſcence, which may
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:153725:65"/> ſatisfy all Thirſt, and all Deſires; which may make thee one Spirit with thy God, which may become in thee a Well of Water ſpringing up to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life, that thou mayeſt ſend thy Services thither before, where thou ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt thy ſelf to abide to endleſs Ages.</p>
               <p>Not without cauſe did the Son of God ſay, <hi>You being evil, know how to give good Gifts to your Children; how much more ſhall your Father in Heaven give his good Spirit to them that ask it?</hi> And he ſaid not, will give Bread, or Raiment, or Wiſdom, or Charity, or the Kingdom of Heaven, or eternal Life, but he ſaid, <hi>will give his good Spirit;</hi> becauſe in that all things are contain'd. Thou therefore ceaſe not daily to mind the Father of his Son's Promiſe, and to ſay with mighty Affection, and an undoubted hope of obtaining, O holy Father, not in confidence of mine own Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but truſting in the Promiſe of thine only begotten Son, do I pour out my Prayers to thee. 'Twas he that ſaid to us, <hi>How much more ſhall
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:153725:65"/> your Father give his good Spirit to them that ask him?</hi> aſſuredly thy Son which is Truth it ſelf, cannot deceive: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore fulfil the Promiſe of thy Son, who glorified thee upon Earth, being every where obedient unto Death, even the Death of the Croſs; give thy holy Spirit to me who ask it, give me the Spirit of thy Fear and Love, that thy Servant may fear nothing but to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend thee, and may love nothing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides thee, and his Neighbour in thee: <hi>Create in me a clean Heart, O God, and renew a right Spirit within me. Caſt me not away from thy Preſence, and take not thy holy Spirit from me. Reſtore unto me the Joy of thy Salvation, and uphold me with thy free Spirit.</hi> Pſal. 51.10, 11, 12.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <p>I Come now to the Similitude the Fountains of Water have with God; for from hence the Mind may be raiſed up to the Contemplation of the truly wonderful and excellent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of him that made them. For
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:153725:66"/> not without juſt cauſe is God in holy Scripture called, <hi>The Fountain of Life,</hi> and the <hi>Fountain of Wiſdom, and Fountain of living Water;</hi> Pſal. 35. Eccleſ. 1. Jer. 2.13. And that he is the very Fountain of being, may be gathered from the Words of God to <hi>Moſes,</hi> Exod. 3. <hi>I am that I am: he that is hath ſent me to you.</hi> The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſeems to comprehend all theſe together when he ſaith, <hi>in him we live, and move, and have our Being;</hi> for in him we are, as in the Fountain of being, in him we live as in the Fountain of Life, in him we move as in the Fountain of Wiſdom: for more moveable is Wiſdom than all things moveable, and by its Purity reacheth every where, as is ſaid in the Book of Wiſdom, <hi>Chap.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>A Fountain of Water hath with us this proper to it ſelf, that from it the Rivers ariſe; and if the Fountains ceaſe to feed them, they preſently dry up; but the Fountain depends not on the Streams, for it receives not its Waters from them, but hath
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:153725:66"/> them in it ſelf, and communicate them to them. This is the true Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bol and Reſemblance of the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, for God is the trueſt Fountain of being; ſeeing he receives being from no other thing, and all receive from him. God receives from nothing, <hi>to be,</hi> becauſe it is the Eſſence of God to be, and Eſſence it ſelf is his Exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence, that it can neither be, nor be conceived in our Thoughts, that God ſhould not have always exiſted, or not always to exiſt; other things may be a while, and a while after ceaſe to be, becauſe <hi>to be,</hi> does not neceſſarily belong to their Eſſence: as for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; it is of the Eſſence of a Man to be a reaſonable Creature, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he cannot be a Man, and not be a reaſonable Creature; and if Exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence were of the Eſſence of a Man, it were impoſſible he ſhould not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways exiſt; but becauſe it is not of his Eſſence to exiſt, therefore he may be, or ceaſe to be. God is therefore the Fountain of being, becauſe actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Exiſtence is included in his very
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:153725:67"/> Eſſence and this do thoſe words ſignify, <hi>I am that I am,</hi> that is, I am Being it ſelf, and receive it not from others, but have it in my ſelf; to me alone it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs, that my very Eſſence is to be. And hence it is that Eternity and Immortality are peculiarly proper un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, as ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>To the King eternal, immortal, the only wiſe God,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.17. <hi>Who only hath Immortality;</hi> 1 Tim. 6.16.</p>
               <p>But all things ſo receive their Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from God, that unleſs they always depend on him, and be preſerved by his Concourſe, they forthwith would ceaſe to be. Hence the ſame Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>upholding all things by the Word of his Power;</hi> becauſe, unleſs God ſhould ſuſtain the Creatures, they could not ſubſiſt.</p>
               <p>Therefore, O my Soul, adore and wonder at the infinite Goodneſs of thy Maker, who ſo lovingly bears up and preſerveth all things, tho he need them not; and do not leſs admire and imitate the Patience of the ſame thy Creator, who is ſo kind to the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:153725:67"/> unthankful and the evil, that he ſuſtains them that blaſpheme him, and upholds them that deſerve to be reduc'd to nothing; neither let it ſeem grievous unto thee, that thou art ſometime required to bear with the Infirmities of thy Brethren, and to do good to them that hate thee.</p>
               <p>Neither is this the only Prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence of him that is the Fountain of Being, that he receives his Being from no other Fountain, and communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates to all other things their Being. For with us the Waters of the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, and the Waters of the Rivers, are of the ſame kind: and altho the Waters of the Fountains receive not their Waters from other Fountains, yet have they ſome other cauſes of their Being, to wit, the Vapours; and they again have other cauſes, till we arrive at the firſt Cauſe, which is God.</p>
               <p>But O my Soul, God that is thy Creator, is not of the ſame kind with created things, but ſtands at an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite diſtance of Dignity and Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:153725:68"/> and Excellency from them; and truly and properly is the Fountain of Being, becauſe he not only receiveth not his Being from any other Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, or Being, but is wholly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any cauſe.</p>
               <p>A Fountain of created Water, as it was ſaid, is not from other Water, yet is derived from another cauſe; the uncreated Fountain of Being, hath nothing before him, depends on nothing, needeth nothing, nothing can hurt him, but all depend on him, and he can extinguiſh all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted things with one wink of his Eye, as ſaith the moſt valiant <hi>Macca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Admire, O my Soul, this Eminence, this Beginning without Beginning, this Cauſe without a Cauſe, this infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, illimited, immenſe, and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary Being, in compariſon of whom all other Beings are meer Contingencies; and it may be Truth it ſelf ſpake of him when he ſaid, But <hi>one thing is neceſſary:</hi> therefore cleave to this One, and ſerve him
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:153725:68"/> only, and delight thy ſelf in the love and deſire of him alone, and in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of him deſpiſe all other things, at leaſt be little ſollicitous about ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things, ſeeing but one thing is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, and that alone may be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient both for thy ſelf and all others. But let this be thy only care, that thou mayeſt never fall from his Grace, and ſtudy always and every-where to pleaſe him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <p>MOreover, God is moſt rightly called the Fountain of Life, becauſe he lives and hath Life in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, yea, is himſelf Eternal Life; <hi>This is the true God, and eternal Life,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>John,</hi> Epiſt. 1. <hi>Chap.</hi> 5.20. And all things which live, receive Life from this Fountain: and if he ceaſe to communicate Life to them, they periſh, and return unto their Duſt, as ſings the holy Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid.</hi> It is the Property of all things which have Life, to beget what is
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:153725:69"/> like unto themſelves: thus God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets his Son moſt like himſelf, God God, and Living Living, <hi>Deus Deum, &amp; vivens viventem;</hi> for <hi>as the Father hath Life in himſelf, ſo hath he given to the Son to have Life in himſelf,</hi> John 5.26. Now the Father hath life in himſelf, becauſe he is the Fountain of Life, and receives not Life from any other; and hath given to the Son to have Life in himſelf, becauſe he hath given him the ſame Life which he himſelf hath; and for this reaſon the Son alſo is a Fountain of Life, but a Fountain of Life from the Fountain of Life, as he is God of God, and Light of Light. Who can explain, yea who can conceive what kind of Life the Life of God is, and what kind of Fountain of Life that is, from whence all things that live either in the Earth, or the Heavens, do draw all their drops? That Life which we in this ſtate of Exile know, is nothing elſe but an internal Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Motion: for thoſe things are ſaid by us to live which ſome way
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:153725:69"/> move themſelves. Hence by way of Similitude they are called <hi>Living Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> which flow in Rivers, and <hi>dead,</hi> which ſtagnate in Ponds; beeauſe thoſe ſeem to be mov'd of themſelves, theſe cannot move, unleſs they be driven by the Winds, or ſome other external force.</p>
               <p>Thy God, O my Soul, moſt truly lives, and is the Author and Spring of Life; for himſelf in holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture often intimates ſo much, <hi>I live, ſaith the Lord;</hi> and the Prophets of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten repeat, <hi>The Lord liveth, The Lord liveth;</hi> and in <hi>Jeremy</hi> God complains of his People, ſaying, <hi>They have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken me the Fountain of Living Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;</hi> and yet he is mov'd neither of himſelf, nor of any other. <hi>I the Lord change not,</hi> Mal. 3. and elſewhere, <hi>God is not a Man that he ſhould lie, nor the Son of Man that he ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, or be changed.</hi> And there is a Hymn ſung daily in the Latin Church to this effect.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:153725:70"/>
                  <l>God who ſtrongly all maintaineſt,</l>
                  <l>In thy ſelf unmov'd remaineſt,</l>
                  <l>Bounding the times of each days light,</l>
                  <l>With the ſucceſſion of the Night.</l>
               </q>
               <p>And altho God begets his Son, he begets him without change; altho he ſees, hears, ſpeaks, loves, pities, judges, he does all without Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; altho he creates and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves things, or on the contrary deſtroys and ſcatters them, and again renews and changeth them, yet he works reſting, and changeth other things without being mov'd; how therefore does he live if he move not himſelf? And how lives he not, if he be the Fountain and Author of Life? This knot is eaſily untied; this is abſolutely ſufficient to Life, if the thing that lives act of it ſelf, and be not moved by another. But Life for the moſt part in created things, is a Principle of inward Motion, becauſe created things are imperfect, and want many things to perform the Functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:153725:70"/> of Life: but God is infinite Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and needs nothing out of himſelf; wherefore he indeeds acts of himſelf, and not moved by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but has no need of Motion or Change, needs not Motion or Muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Created things need Change, that they may generate and be gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, becauſe they beget out of themſelves; and the thing that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten muſt be chang'd from not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into being; but God begets his Son within himſelf, and within him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf proceeds his holy Spirit, and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Son or Holy Ghoſt ought to be chang'd from not being unto be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, becauſe they receive that Being that always was; and that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive not in time, but in Eternity. Created things want motion of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, becauſe they were born im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect; but God the Son is born moſt perfect; and God the Holy Ghoſt is breath'd forth alſo, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd moſt perfect. Created things need the motion of Alteration, that they may obtain the various Qualities
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:153725:71"/> they want: but God wants nothing, ſeeing his Eſſence is of infinite Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. Created things want local motion, becauſe they are not every<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where; but God is every-where wholly.</p>
               <p>Further; Created things that they may ſee, that they may hear, that they may ſpeak, that they may work, want many things; becauſe tho in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they have Life, yet it is imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and very poor: but God wants nothing out of himſelf, that he may ſee all things, hear all, ſpeak to all, and work all in all, becauſe he not only hath Life, but the Life he hath is moſt opulent and happy, and he himſelf is Life, and the Fountain of Life. And that we may give an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample in the act of ſeeing: a Man that he may ſee, muſt have a viſive Power, which is diſtinct from the Soul, which properly lives; he muſt have an Object, ſome colour'd Body plac'd without himſelf; he muſt have the Light of the Sun, or ſome other luminous Body; he muſt have a <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium,</hi>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:153725:71"/> ſome diaphanous Body; he muſt have a ſenſible Species, which may be carried from the Object to the Eye; he muſt have a corporal Organ, that is, an Eye ſitly made of various Humours and fleſhy Tunicles; he muſt have ſenſitive Spirits, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Nerves, through which thoſe Spirits may paſs; he muſt have a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proportion'd diſtance; and after all, muſt apply his Power to the act of Seeing. Behold how many helps both Men and other Creatures want, that they may perform one vital Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: but God who truly hath Life wholly in himſelf, wants nothing at all. His infinite Eſſence is to him Power, Object, Species, Light and all things elſe of himſelf, and by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and in himſelf; God ſees and clearly diſcovers all things which are, which have been, which ſhall be, and which can be; and before the World was made God ſaw all things, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did any thing new accrue unto his Sight or Knowledg by the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all things. What therefore
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:153725:72"/> ſhalt thou be, O my Soul, when thou ſhalt be partaker of his Life? what great matter does God command thee, when he requires thee to lay down this corporal, this animal Life, which is ſo imperfect and full of wants, for thy Brethren, and for God himſelf, that thou mayeſt be made partaker of Eternal Life, which is moſt rich and bleſſed? And if it be a ſmall matter he requires, when he requires thee to deſpiſe Life, how ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry light and little ſhould it ſeem, when he bids thee to diſtribute thy dead Riches liberally to the Poor, to abſtain from carnal Luſts, truly to renounce the Devil and his Pomps; and with thy whole Heart to breath after that Life, which alone is Life indeed, and Truth?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <p>BUT now 'tis time, that as well as we can, we aſcend unto the Fountain of Wiſdom. The Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of Wiſdom is the Word of God
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:153725:72"/> in the higheſt, ſaith <hi>Eccleſiaſticus;</hi> and well he ſaid in the Higheſt, becauſe the Fountain of Wiſdom abundantly and copiouſly flows forth upon the holy Angels, and the Souls of the Bleſſed, whoſe Habitations are the higheſt Heavens. To us who are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant in this Pilgrimage and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſart, not ſo much Wiſdom it ſelf, as a ſlight ſcent and ſhadow of it is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainable. Wherefore, O my Soul, affect not things too much above thee; ſearch not the Majeſty leſt thou be oppreſſed of the Glory. Admire his Wiſdom of whom the Apoſtle ſpeaks; <hi>To God only wiſe,</hi> Rom. 16. and gratulate thoſe bleſſed Souls that drink out of the Fountain of Wiſdom: and tho they cannot comprehend God, which is proper to the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of Wiſdom it ſelf, yet they ſee the Face of God, that is, of the firſt cauſe without any interpoſed Vail, and being irradiated by the Beams of his Brightneſs, can judg rightly of all things; and in that noon-day Light of Wiſdom, fear neither the
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:153725:73"/> Darkneſs of Errors, nor Obſcurity of Ignorance, nor the Dimneſs of Opinions. Aſpire, O my Soul, unto that Happineſs. And that thou mayeſt ſafely attain it, love with all thy Heart, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, in whom are hidden all the Treaſures of the Knowledg and Wiſdom of God, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.3. for he hath ſaid in his Goſpel, <hi>He that loveth me, ſhall be loved of my Father, and I will love him, and manifeſt my ſelf to him,</hi> John 14.21. And what elſe doth this ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie, <hi>I will manifeſt my ſelf to him,</hi> but I will manifeſt all the Treaſures of the Knowledg and Wiſdom of God, which lie hid in me? Aſſuredly eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man naturally deſires to know; and tho carnal Luſts do in many lull theſe deſires aſleep, yet when we have put off this Body that corrupts and preſſes down our Soul, then will the Fire of this Deſire blaze forth above all Deſires. How great will then thy Happineſs, O my Soul, be, when thy Beloved and thy Lover <hi>CHRIST,</hi> will ſhew thee all the
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:153725:73"/> Treaſures of the Knowledg and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God? But that ſuch hopes may not be fruſtrate, ſtrive to keep Chriſt's Precepts, for he hath ſaid, <hi>If any Man loves me, he will keep my Words; and he that loves me not, keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not my Words.</hi> Mean while, let thy Wiſdom be ſuch as holy <hi>Job</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes, <hi>The Fear of the Lord is Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; and to depart from evil, is <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding.</hi> And what good ſoever thou beholdeſt in the Creatures, know that it flows from God, the Fountain of all Goodneſs, and ſo with bleſſed <hi>Francis,</hi> learn to to taſte the Goodneſs of the Fountain in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Creature, as in Rivolets that are derived from it.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="prayers">
            <pb facs="tcp:153725:74"/>
            <pb n="117" facs="tcp:153725:74"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Devotions for Water-drinkers: OR,</hi> Meditations, Prayers, and Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving fitted to that occaſion.</head>
            <div n="1" type="meditation">
               <head>
                  <hi>MEDITATION I.</hi> Upon the many kinds of Diſeaſes cured by theſe Waters.</head>
               <p>HOW great is that Evil which Fools make a Mock of? The Cauſe may be ſeen in the Effects. Had there been no Sin, there had been no Sorrow, nor Sickneſs, no Diſeaſes, Pain, or Death. The great number of Diſtempers is no ſmall evidence of the great Evil of Sin. 'Tis a prolifick Root which bears ſuch vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, ſuch multitude of Fruit. The great Phyſician <hi>Fernelius</hi> cries out,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:153725:75"/> 
                  <hi>Totus Homo, totus Morbus,</hi> which we may engliſh by the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi>'s Words, <hi>From the ſole of the Foot e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the Head there is no Soundneſs:</hi> and not only from top to bottom, but from outſide to within, <hi>the whole Head is ſick, and the whole Heart is faint.</hi> And the Prince of Phyſicians, <hi>Galen,</hi> ſums up the Diſeaſes to which the Eye alone is ſubject, to amount to no leſs than three hundred: how many then of the whole Head? how many are there of the whole Body? And yet the moſt of what we know, is the leaſt of what we know not. How many hidden Diſtempers, and which yet know no Name, are we ſubject to? And Art is poſed to keep pace with Nature, and fit new Names to new Diſeaſes. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt every Year, ſome comes upon the Stage known by no other dreſs, call'd by no other title but the <hi>New Fever,</hi> or <hi>New Diſeaſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And yet, O Lord, the number of our Sins, which exceed the number of our Diſeaſes, is more exceeded by the
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:153725:75"/> multitude of thy Mercies, than the Stars outſhine the Gloworms, or thy Throne in Heaven is higher than thy Foot-ſtool on Earth.</p>
               <p>He's blind which doth not ſee, he deſerves to be ſtruck dumb who will not confeſs this Truth, which every day, which every place proclaims; but few more loudly or ſignificantly than this Place or Seaſon. How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Miracles of Mercy doth thy Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Goodneſs daily work here? How many Patients wait upon thee the Great Phyſician? How many chronical and ſtubborn Diſtempers, which had baffled all the Sons of Art, yield to the God of Nature? Should the vaſt number, which dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly drink of this Fountain of thy Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, ſtrictly confer Notes, their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers would be found as different as their Faces, not two exactly alike, yet all expect, and moſt obtain Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief? O Lord, by the multitude of thy unknown Mercies, heal all the known, and unknown Diſeaſes of our Bodies, and Sins of our Souls.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="meditation">
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:153725:76"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>MEDITAT. II. With Alluſion to</hi> 
                  <bibl>John <hi>5.3.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>In them lay a multitude of Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Folk, waiting for the moving of the Water.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THE mighty Confluence, of which theſe Wells are the Centre, is a very humbling, a very mortifying Conſideration. For tho the Gallantry and Rich Attire of the Company, may emulate the Courts of greateſt Princes, and make this Deſert forget its Solitude; and we may in this Wilderneſs find ſuch Soft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Delicacy, as uſes to be in King's Houſes: Yet in very truth this place is but a great Hoſpital, and the ſplendid Buildings which riſe ſo faſt, at <hi>South-borough, Ruſt-Hall</hi> and about <hi>Mount-Ephraim,</hi> are but ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Apartments in this great Infirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory. And the Gueſts who fill them are but ſo many Impotent <hi>Lazars,</hi>
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:153725:76"/> under the Veſts of <hi>Dives.</hi> Every Glaſs we drink for cure is a tacite Confeſſion of our hidden Infirmities and inward Diſtempers; and that tho array'd as the Lillies of the Field, as very Graſs as they. Gay Beggars which wait at theſe <hi>Wells,</hi> which are the Celler of the great Houſe-keeper for a dole of Mercy. Nothing is more inſufferable than an inſolent Beggar: Nothing more deſpicable than to be poor and proud; to need Relief, and provoke him from whom we expect it. The firſt Preſcription every wiſe Phyſician gives his Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent is, that he muſt be regular: take what he orders, and as he orders. Thou, Lord, art our Phyſician, we are thy Patients; theſe Wells are thy Shop, their Waters are thy Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines; thy Word the Preſcription how we muſt uſe them (and all thy other Gifts) with Prayer and Thanks-giving. O that we all may humbly and ſincerely do ſo! <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="meditation">
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:153725:77"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>MEDITAT. III.</hi> Upon an Herſe paſsing by towards the Wells, <hi>July 22.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BEing return'd to my Lodgings from the Wells, and ſitting in the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Tent of my honoured Friend, I ſaw an Herſe paſs towards the Wells. And tho I had not heard of the Death of any Perſon of Quality here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts, yet it put me in mind of a Paſſage of the wiſe Moraliſt <hi>Seneca,</hi> which I think (for I dare not affirm it at this diſtance from my Books) is in 101 Epiſt. wrote on the ſudden Death of <hi>Senecio.</hi> 
                  <q>Becauſe thou knoweſt not when Death will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect thee, do thou expect it in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry time: and becauſe thou knoweſt not where it will meet thee, do thou look for it in every place.</q> 'Tis in hope of Health and Life that Men come hither; yet ſome who come down in a Coach, have changed it
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:153725:77"/> for an Herſe to be carried up in; and when they were knocking at the Doors of Health, had the the Gates of the Grave unlock'd to receive them, and found what was ordained for Life to be unto Death. O how good, how wiſe is it, to be always prepared to die, and every day to ſtrike Tallies with Life! O Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, who wilt certainly be my Judg when I die, give me Wiſdom, give me thy Grace to take thy Counſel while I live, while I am in Health to be always ready, as a wiſe Virgin, for the coming of the Bridegroom. <hi>Bleſſed is that Servant whom his Lord when he comes ſhall find watching.</hi> Good Lord vouchſafe to make me of that happy number. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="meditation">
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:153725:78"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>MEDITAT. IV.</hi> Upon the plentiful Supply with which God hath furniſhed the World both for Food and Phyſick.</head>
               <p>'TIs a great Aggravation of our Sins that we commit them all againſt our Benefactor, and abuſe all the Creatures of God to his Diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. To take, as the Prophet <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeah</hi> ſpeaks, his Silver, his Gold, his Wooll and his Flax, his Bread and his Fleſh, his Wine, and his Water, his Time and his Talents, and to turn them againſt himſelf, and as with Weapons of Unrighteouſneſs to fight againſt him.</p>
               <p>Yet, O Lord, ſo inconquerable is thy Goodneſs, that thy Patience ſeconds thy Bounty, in continuing to us what our ill Deſerts have forfeited, as thou gav'ſt it freely without any good De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert of ours. And not only in ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying our bare Neceſſities, but fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:153725:78"/> of us for Convenience, for Pleaſure and Delight; yea for reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of thoſe Diſtempers which we poſſibly have brought upon our ſelves by the abuſe of thy own Bleſſings: for the whole World is thy well-ſtor'd Shop, and every Element is furniſh'd with Supply: The Air with Fowls, the Water with Fiſh, the Earth with ſmall and great Cattel, and with a numberleſs variety of Plants and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals; and the Fire is the common Servant to them all, to concoct their Crudities, to dreſs and make them fit for Uſe and Nouriſhment: Neither are they leſs apt for Phyſick than for Food, for Medicine than for Meat.</p>
               <p>To paſs the reſt in a grateful, tho ſilent Admiration; The Fountains are not only thy Cellars to quench our Thirſt; but thy Baths and thy Alimbecks, where Almighty Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is the Operator, and the God of Nature prevents the Trouble and Charge of Art.</p>
               <p>O let this thy Goodneſs at length conquer the Obſtinacy of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:153725:79"/> that our Ingratitude and Provocations may never overcome thy Clemency and Patience; that we may be ſo weary and aſham'd of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning againſt thee, that thou mayeſt never be weary, nor repent the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of us good. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="meditation">
               <head>
                  <hi>MEDITAT. V.</hi> Upon the Water of Jealouſy, <bibl>
                     <hi>Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> the <hi>5th.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </head>
               <p>THere are many righteous Laws, and ſevere Threatnings in holy Scripture, of the Execution of which we meet with no recorded Inſtance or Example. Such is that of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious Son being ſton'd to death up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Parents Complaint of him, and teſtifying againſt him for his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience; <hi>Deut.</hi> 21.18. And that of the bitter Water to be drunk by the Wife of the jealous Huſband, (which Water was to be mixt with
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:153725:79"/> the Duſt of the Floor of the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle, probably to make the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Sins Anagram; and to ſignify it ſhould not fail of its dire Effects on them who trampled under foot the Authority of him who dwelt in it) which cauſed her Belly to ſwell, and Thigh to rot, who was defiled: <hi>Numb.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>There is a great Affinity and Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs between God's Books of his Word, and of his Works: the Laws of both have righteous Sanctions ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther expreſſed or imply'd; and tho we read not Examples of the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of thoſe who brake the firſt, nor have obſerved inſtances of their Miſery who have tranſgreſt the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, yet aſſuredly wilful Offenders. ſhall not eſcape the ſmart and burden of vindictive Juſtice.</p>
               <p>O my Soul, thy Maker is thy Huſband, provoke him not to Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſy; let not the Impunity of others imbolden thee: they may feel that (thoſe <hi>ſurda verbera</hi>) which thou canſt take no notice of, or he who ſees
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:153725:80"/> their day is coming, may reſerve ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verer Wrath againſt that day. What ever others do, do thou thy Duty. Love flows in theſe Waters; make ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table returns of Love: Provoke not him whoſe Help thou always needeſt, and here moſt ſignally expecteſt, not only leſt thy Hopes abuſe thee with a Diſappointment, but the expected Bleſſing be turn'd into a Curſe; and inſtead of opening Obſtructions, and yielding Help and Health, they make thy Belly ſwell, and occaſion Sorrow, Pain and Death.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="meditation">
               <head>MEDITAT. VI.</head>
               <p>WHen I obſerve the great Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities of Water drunk every Morning at theſe Wells, it calls to my mind that Expreſſion of <hi>David,</hi> of ſome who drink Iniquity like Water. Luſt is a very thirſty and inſatiable thing, it never ſaith it is enough; 'tis an hydropick Sickneſs
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:153725:80"/> of the Soul: the more it drinks the more it thirſts. The Fountain of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption cannot be ſtopt, it is impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent of a Damm. If one Outlet be ſhut, it will find or make another. But O how poiſonous, how deadly are thoſe draughts it ſwallows down with ſo greedy a delight? We here drink innocent Healths. But ſuch Men drink much worſe than <hi>Circean</hi> Cups, their own Damnation. How can any Sinner hope for impunity, when eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Sin carries its own Hell, a bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs deſire after more? And O moſt Righteous Lord, 'tis juſt and equal that they who have forſaken Thee the ſatisfying Fountain of Living Waters, ſhould weary themſelves in their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring after Diſappointment, in hewing out ſuch broken Ciſterns as can hold no Water. O Thou who haſt given me a Soul capable of thy Self, and incapable of reſt till it reſt in thy ſelf, who art the Center of its Being and Deſires, draw me to thy Self, fit me for thy Self, fill me with thy Self; give me to drink of thoſe Waters
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:153725:81"/> of Paradiſe, every drop of which is bigger than the Ocean. Give me to hunger and thirſt after Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and I have the Security of his Word, who cannot lie, that I ſhall be ſatisfied; that having a Well of Water in my ſelf, derived from thee the living Fountain, I may thirſt no more with an uneaſy, vexing, deadly Thirſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="meditation">
               <head>MEDITAT. VII.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Ezek. 47.9.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>—And every thing ſhall live whither the River cometh.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THe latter part of this Prophet is ſo dark, that all Interpreters are ready to cry out, as I remember <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſianus</hi> doth, when he comes to it, I now enter into the thick darkneſs. 'Tis no wonder therefore that the heads of that River, which brake out in thoſe Regions of Obſcurity, ſhould be more hidden than thoſe of <hi>Nile;</hi> yet undoubtedly this is that River which <hi>David</hi> ſaith <hi>makes glad the City
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:153725:81"/> of God;</hi> and which he elſewhere calls <hi>the River of his Pleaſure.</hi> What can this be but thoſe Waters of the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary which flow from the Throne of God and the Lamb, the Graces and Comforts of thy Spirit? O let that Bleſſed Spirit, which proceedeth from the Father and the Son, and whom the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed teacheth us to call <hi>the Lord and Giver of Life,</hi> come down upon us, and effect more in and for our Souls, than we expect or look for to our Bodies, from the Waters of theſe Wells; that by the coming of this River to us, we may live the life of Grace here, and may be fitted for the Life of Everlaſting Glory hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="meditation">
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:153725:82"/>
               <head>MEDITAT. VIII. <hi>Upon</hi> 
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2</hi> Kings <hi>5.12.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>Are not <hi>Abana</hi> and <hi>Pharphar,</hi> Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> better than all the Waters of <hi>Iſrael?</hi> May I not waſh in them, and be clean? and he went away in a rage. <hi>With verſ. 17.</hi> — Thy Servant will henceforth offer neither Burnt-Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering nor Sacrifice unto other Gods, but unto the LORD.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THere's not a greater difference betwixt the Waters in which he waſh'd, and the Fire by which he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered burnt Sacrifice, than between the Sentiments and Language of the <hi>Syrian</hi> Leper, and the cleanſed Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyte. How did the Rage of his inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Mind flame out at his diſdainful Lips? But when that <hi>Jordan</hi> which
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:153725:82"/> waſh'd his Body, had baptiz'd his Soul, healing both, with how ſedate a Calmneſs, and humble and reſolved Firmneſs doth he devote himſelf to <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s God, and to the Rights of his before deſpiſed Worſhip?</p>
               <p>Tho right Reaſon be the Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid of Devotion, and the beſt Stock on which to graft Religion, (for nothing is more reaſonable, than that God ſhould communicate his Grace in his own Methods, and receive our Homage according to his own Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointments,) yet carnal Reaſon, truly ſo call'd, corrupt and blinded with the malignant Influence, and ſelfiſh Intereſt of Fleſh and Blood, dares rival God's Wiſdom, and more than mate his Authority, deride it.</p>
               <p>It would perhaps ſound harſh if ſome of us ſhould ask, Are not other Waters better than theſe of <hi>Tunbridg-Wells?</hi> How uncomely is it then to depreſs the Wells of <hi>Sion</hi> below the Ciſterns of Sins and Creatures? yet how many <hi>Abana</hi>'s and <hi>Pharphar</hi>'s do moſt prefer before God's <hi>Jordan?</hi>
                  <pb n="134" facs="tcp:153725:83"/> not only deſecrating the Waters con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated to the myſtical waſhing away of Sin, (and all his other holy Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions) by diſbeliving God's good Promiſes, and neglecting to make good their own, but the very Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain from which they were derived, that opened for Sin and for Unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the ſide of Chriſt?</p>
               <p>Not only the ſtagnant Pool of our Unrighteouſneſs, and the broken Ciſterns of Creature Comforts; but the cleaneſt Streams of our beſt Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſes, are Waters of <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> compar'd to the Blood and Spirit of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>O my Soul, take heed thou equal none of them with Him in thy E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem and Love. And O my God, give me ſuch a ſenſe of my worthleſs Emptineſs as may make me profoundly humble! And that Humility will make me thankful, and that Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs will inflame my Love, and that Love will conſtrain my Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to a willing obſervance of all thy Inſtitutions, becauſe they bear the
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:153725:83"/> Image and Inſcription of thy Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, of thy Wiſdom and thy Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; who art thy ſelf the Fountain of every Stream that is deſirable and good. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="meditation">
               <head>MEDITAT. IX. <hi>Upon</hi> 
                  <bibl>Pſal. <hi>87.7.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>All my Springs are in thee.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>GOD is often called a Rock by <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the Prophets; but eſpecially by <hi>David;</hi> and there's good reaſon for that Appellation: for there's no Creature, that hath not Life, that hath more, and more live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Reſemblances of his Nature, and Properties. He is a ſtrong Refuge, a firm Foundation, a refreſhing Shade, a ſecure Hiding-place. But moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minently, all Springs of Goodneſs are in Him, and iſſue from him, as Waters from a Rock. All our Springs
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:153725:84"/> are in him, of Life, and Being, of Food and Raiment, of Meat and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, of preſervation in Health, and recovery out of Sickneſs. Theſe nether-Springs, O Lord, guſh out upon us by the unlocking of thy Treaſuries.</p>
               <p>But more eſpecially thoſe upper Springs of Grace and Comfort, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and Peace: And above all, the Bleſſing of theſe Bleſſings to us, and rendring of them, what we pray they may be, Bleſſings indeed.</p>
               <p>O Lord my God, thy Goodneſs is the rich Mineral, through which our Springs do glide! 'tis this which gives them, both their Tincture and their Taſte, renders them wholſom, makes them healthful. O that this may impregnate all the Streams which flow ſo freely to us, may rectify, may ſanctify, may bleſs them to us, that we may bleſs and glorify thy holy Name in that behalf for ever! <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="meditation">
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:153725:84"/>
               <head>MEDITAT. X. <hi>Upon</hi> 
                  <bibl>Rev. <hi>22.17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>The Spirit and the Bride ſay, Come; and whoſoever will, let him take the Waters of Life freely.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>VVHatever is beneficial, inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuates it ſelf to prove In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive, and thereby acquires a Right to be ſo; and by doing of us good, obligeth us to be good.</p>
               <p>Theſe Waters have a Voice, and joyn the <hi>Chorus,</hi> which ecchoing the call of the Spirit, and the Bride, (the Church on Earth, and God from Heaven) invite us to come and take of the Waters of Life freely. The Perennity of their Streams, the free acceſs that, from the Prince to the Peaſant, all have to them; their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual Helpfulneſs to rich and poor, to bad and good; and many more like Properties, are all inſtructive.
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:153725:85"/> They heal no bodily Infirmity, which hath not ſome Diſtemper of our Souls, to be relieved by thoſe living Waters.</p>
               <p>They teach us Perſeverance and Conſtancy in doing well, that our Goodneſs be not as the Morning-Dew, but, like their laſting Streams, to yield a free approach to thoſe who need our Help; to be ready to diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, willing to communicate, to be forward to do good to all.</p>
               <p>O my Soul, exemplify their Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, and improve the advantages thy Body hath obtained by their uſe to the like helping of the inward Man. Have they waſh'd out the Slime, the Sand, the Gravel, and heal'd or eas'd thee of the Stone? Let it melt thy ſtony Heart into an Heart of fleſh: and be encouraged hence to believe, and ſue out into Performances, the Promiſes of the Covenant of Grace (which are the Springs of Salvation) from the Experience of God's ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling what his Providence doth ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citely promiſe, by theſe natural Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains;
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:153725:85"/> Experience breeds Hope. Have they begot an Appetite? Hunger and thirſt thou after Righteouſneſs. Have they ſweetned the Blood, thin'd it, and made it circulate, opened and remov'd Obſtructions? put thou away all Superfluity of Naughtineſs, all Rancor, Malice and Revenge: fill up the circle of univerſal Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and let nothing hinder the Grace of God from having a free courſe through all thy Faculties. Have theſe cut the tough, the viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cous Humours? let thoſe better Waters cut the Iron Sinew, till thy Neck willingly bow to the ſweet, to the eaſy Yoke of Chriſt. Have they rendred any fruitful? let the barren Soul endeavour to have Chriſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in it, that it may bring forth Fruit to God. Have they cooled thoſe Heats you call Heart-burnings? Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply theſe Waters of Life to the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriz'd Conſcience, ſear'd as with an hot Iron; that theſe may quench the Burning, mollify the Tumour, cica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trize the Wound, till your Hearts
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:153725:86"/> be cured of an evil Conſcience, to ſerve the living God with Purity and Peace. O my Soul hear thou theſe kind, theſe gracious Invitations. And O my God, circumciſe my Heart, that I may cloſe with them; and what thou offereſt ſo freely, give effectually, and help me to receive thankfully, and improve ſavingly, that they may be indeed the Waters of Life in Grace and Glory, that I may thirſt no more. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>The end of the Meditations.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayers">
            <pb n="141" facs="tcp:153725:86"/>
            <head>Some Forms of <hi>PRAYER</hi> and <hi>THANKSGIVING</hi> to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the Devotion of thoſe who drink the Waters of <hi>Tunbridg-Wells,</hi> or wait upon God's Providence in the uſe of other Mineral Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains.</head>
            <div n="1" type="prayer">
               <head>PRAYER I.</head>
               <p>O Almighty God, and our moſt merciful Father in Jeſus Chriſt, who by the Mouth of him thy deareſt Son haſt taught us, that Man lives not by Bread only, but by the Word which proceedeth out of thy Mouth. We know that dead things cannot give us Life without the Influence
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:153725:87"/> and Bleſſing of Thee, who art the living God; nor any preparations of Art or Nature heal us, without thy Healing Concurrence, who ſtileſt thy Self, <hi>The Lord that healeth.</hi> We there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore moſt humbly beſeech thee, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company with thy Bleſſing, and to crown with a deſided and merciful Succeſs, the uſe we make of theſe <hi rend="blackletterType">Medicinal Waters;</hi> that they may occaſion neither Sin nor Sickneſs, nor any Inconvenience to us: but prove uſeful and beneficial to us, for the continuance, reſtauration, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of Health to our frail Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. And as we beg thy leave to uſe, thy Grace to uſe aright, and thy Bleſſing upon the uſe of, theſe Waters of the nether Springs: So with hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble earneſtneſs we beg, that the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Sanctuary, which flow from the Throne of the Lamb of God, the promiſed Floods of thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit, may be plentifully poured forth upon us, to refreſh, to ſatisfie, to cleanſe, to heal our parched, weary, and polluted Souls: that ſo both with
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:153725:87"/> our Bodies and our Spirits, which thou haſt made by thy Power, and bought with the price of thy Son's Blood, we may glorify Thee our great Creator, and gracious Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="prayer">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>O moſt holy Lord God, who tho Thou art moſt merciful, in providing relieving Remedies for thy Creatures, yet art moſt jealous of thy Glory, and expecteſt to be owned and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged in all the Works of thy Power and Goodneſs to the Sons of Men. We pray thee raiſe up our Hearts by theſe <hi rend="blackletterType">Waters,</hi> and beyond the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of them, to thy Self, whoſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence hath made them what they are. And as we abhor that groſs Idolatry, of worſhipping the likeneſs of any thing that is in the Waters un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Earth: So we pray thee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve us from a more refined, but not leſs criminal Idolatry, of placing our Confidence in their Qualities and
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:153725:88"/> Virtues, and forgetting Thee the Maker of them: leſt we provoke Thee to withdraw the Bleſſing we expect, and inflict the Curſe we have cauſe to fear; and to make them the Inſtruments of thy Vengeance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we made them the Objects of our Truſt, and Occaſions of thy Jealouſie. Grant this, O Lord, for Chriſt his ſake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="prayer">
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>O moſt gracious God, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteſt in Mercy, and pardoneſt Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, Tranſgreſſion and Sin: We thy poor ſinful Creatures humbly caſt down our ſelves before thee; begging the Forgiveneſs of our Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, which may juſtly cauſe thee to with-hold good things from us, yea to turn our Bleſſings into Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; that what is made for the good of others, might become to us a Snare and occaſion of falling But we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee deal not with us according to our deſerts: but bleſs to us the uſe
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:153725:88"/> of theſe Waters, that we may receive thoſe Benefits by them, for which we may have great cauſe to honour, love and ſerve thee for ever. And we pray thee give us good Hearts to do accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly, for thy Mercy ſake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="prayer">
               <head>IV.</head>
               <p>O Lord, who art the Fountain of living Waters, we confeſs with ſhame, we have forſaken Thee, and have hewen out to our ſelves empty and broken Ciſterns, which can hold no Water: for which it might be juſt with thee, to forſake and caſt us off for ever. But good Lord, convince us of this Folly; pardon, and turn us from it. Do us good by theſe <hi rend="blackletterType">Wells</hi> we daily ſee and taſte of, and open our Eyes, as thou didſt the Eyes of <hi>Hagar,</hi> to ſee thoſe Wells of Salvation which are hid from all but thoſe to whom thou art pleaſed to ſhew them: and help us with joy to draw from thence, what may ſo ſuffice and ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie us, that we may thirſt no more. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="prayer">
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:153725:89"/>
               <head>V.</head>
               <p>Almighty God, the Fountain of all Goodneſs; we reade that thy <hi>Manna</hi> reliſht agreeably, and pleaſed the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Palats of all that ate it. O that theſe <hi rend="blackletterType">Waters</hi> may profit every per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that drinks of them, how different ſo ever the Diſtempers are for which they drink them: That thy Wiſdom and Power may more ſignally appear, by thy producing ſuch various Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects from one and the ſame ſingle Cauſe. And help us all who drink of one Well, to be knit together in the Bond of true Chriſtian Charity; and to praiſe thee for the Mercies thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoweſt on our ſelves, and for the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies thou vouchſafeſt unto others, as heartily as for our own; for Chriſt his ſake who is our common Head. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="prayer">
               <head>VI.</head>
               <p>O moſt bleſſed Lord God, who giveſt thy Bleſſings, and alone canſt bleſs thy Gifts: We beſeech thee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:153725:89"/> thy Curſe which our Sins have deſerved, from us, from all our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments, and particularly from theſe <hi rend="blackletterType">Waters</hi> we are gathered hither to make uſe of: and let thy Bleſſing ſo accompany and follow our drinking of them, that we may be both ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged and inabled to praiſe thy Name, through Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="prayer">
               <head>VII.</head>
               <p>O moſt gracious God, who haſt made a gracious Promiſe, that all things ſhall work for the good of them that love thee: ingraft in our Hearts ſuch love to thy Name, as may intitle us to this good Promiſe. And altho we have forfeited our preſent Comforts, and future Expectations of Good; yet take not the Forfeitures we have made, but crown with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Patience, thy former Bounty; and add new Favours, and ſuffer none of us where and while we ſeek for help, and Eaſe, and Health, and Life, to meet with Pain, or Sorrow, Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:153725:90"/> Death and Judgment: But by by theſe <hi rend="blackletterType">Waters</hi> heal our Diſeaſes, and by a better Fountain purge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and pardon all our Sins, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord and only Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="prayer">
               <head>VIII.</head>
               <p>O Lord our God, who art the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exhauſtible Fountain of all both ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and temporal good things, for our Souls, and for our Bodies: we lift up our Hearts and Hands to Thee in Heaven, for a merciful Supply of all our inward and outward Wants, and that Thou wouldſt ſanctify and bleſs to us all thoſe Supplies thy Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs doth vouchſafe us, both for our Souls and Bodies, whether for Meat or Medicine; and particularly theſe <hi rend="blackletterType">Waters,</hi> that they may do us much good, and no hurt; and for all the benefits we receive from Thee, we pray thee inable us to render to Thee ſuch returns of Service, Love, and Thankfulneſs as Thou mayeſt expect,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:153725:90"/> and wilt accept, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="prayer">
               <head>IX.</head>
               <p>O moſt mighty God, who makeſt the <hi rend="blackletterType">Fountains of Waters,</hi> thoſe in the Fields and Deſerts, as Thou art the God of <hi>Nature;</hi> and that in thy Church (the Fountain of our Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm) as Thou art the God of <hi>Grace:</hi> We moſt humbly beſeech Thee bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize us with the Holy Ghoſt, and let it be the conſtant ſtudy of our lives, to keep the Covenant we made with Thee in our Baptiſm; and to exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plify it by ſuch a Converſation as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the Goſpel, receiving by Faith the good Promiſes thou haſt made to us, and making good with faithfulneſs the Promiſes we then made to Thee, to thy Glory, the good example of all our fellow-Chriſtians, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and Salvation of our Souls by Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="prayer">
               <head>X.</head>
               <p>O moſt merciful Lord God, who haſt opened a Fountain for Sin and
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:153725:91"/> for Uncleanneſs in the Side, in the Heart of thy own dear Son; whom Thou ſenteſt into this World to ſave his People from their Sins, from all their Sins, and all that is in Sin. O let nothing be in vain to our Souls of all that he hath done or ſuffered, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted or ordained for his Peoples good. Juſtify us freely in his Blood, ſanctify us throughly by his Spirit; and let him be made of God to us, <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> to preſerve us from the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfulneſs of Sin; <hi>Sanctification,</hi> to deliver us from the filthineſs of Sin; <hi>Redemption,</hi> to free us from the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage and dominion of Sin; and <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs,</hi> to ſave us from the guilt and damnation of Sin; that we may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver periſh, but have Everlaſting Life. All which we beg for his ſake, who is thy Chriſt, and our Jeſus: to whom with thy Self, and thy eternal Spirit, be aſcribed everlaſting Praiſe and Glory for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>The end of the Prayers.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="thanksgivings">
            <pb n="151" facs="tcp:153725:91"/>
            <head>Forms of Thanksgiving.</head>
            <div n="1" type="thanksgiving">
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>O LORD moſt Mighty, the great Creator of all things in Heaven and Earth: whoſe Works are the Witneſſes of Thy Being; and of the adorable Perfections of thy Nature: We bleſs and magnify thy glorious Name for all thy wondrous Works; for making the Heavens and their Hoſt, the Earth, and its Store; the Sea, and all the Waters in it, and that ſpring from it: and in particular for making theſe <hi rend="blackletterType">Healing Fountains;</hi> for making known their Virtues; for giving us liberty to uſe them; and for any Bleſſing formerly, or at this ſeaſon vouchſafed to us by the uſe of them. And we pray Thee to crown theſe Mercies with one better than
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:153725:92"/> the reſt, even ſo thankful an Heart as may improve all to thy Glory, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="thanksgiving">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>O Lord, who art good, and doſt good: We bleſs thy glorious Name for what thou art, and what thou do'ſt; for the Healing Fountain of thy free Grace, and for the free Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of theſe <hi rend="blackletterType">Healing Waters;</hi> for the Bleſſings of thy Throne, and of thy Footſtool; for our Life, and for our Livelihood; for our Food, and for our Phyſick; for the Waters of the upper and the nether Springs; for all thy Fountains, and for all their Streams. Good Lord, create one Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain more, even a Fountain of Love and Thankfulneſs in all our Hearts, and cauſe it to flow with conſtant ſtreams of Obedience and Praiſe, which may be acceptable in thy ſight, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="thanksgiving">
               <pb n="153" facs="tcp:153725:92"/>
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>O Lord, who art pleaſed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, That who-ſo offereth Thee Thanks and Praiſe, honoureth Thee; Accept our unfeigned deſires to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour Thee, by giving thee Thanks and Praiſe with our whole Hearts, and our whole Souls, for thy mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold and ineſtimable Mercies vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed unto us. <hi>Not unto us, Lord, not unto us, but to thy holy Name be given Glory.</hi> We are leſs than the leaſt of thy Mercies: We deſerved none be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we had them: we have forfeited all ſince we had them; yet art thou pleaſed of thy Aſtoniſhing Goodneſs, to give us new Inſtances of Mercy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day; Lord, give us a renewed ſenſe of them all, and an holy Zeal, with humble Hearts to honour Thee for them all; through Him by whom they are conveyed to us, that is, thy Son, our Lord and Saviour, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="thanksgiving">
               <pb n="154" facs="tcp:153725:93"/>
               <head>IV.</head>
               <p>O Almighty and infinitely gracious Lord God, we deſire to fear Thee, to give Thee Glory, and to worſhip Thee that madeſt the Heaven and the Earth, and the Sea and the Fountains of Water; and for making theſe in particular, of which we drink daily with ſo much ſatisfaction, and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of relief: We beſeech Thee let not our Provocations diſappoint our Hopes, but pardon thoſe, and nouriſh theſe, and crown them with a bleſſed ſucceſs; that we may ever give Thee Thanks, and live thy Praiſes, through Chriſt our Lord. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="thanksgiving">
               <head>V.</head>
               <p>What ſhall we render to the Lord for all his Benefits? Let us take the Cup of Salvation and call upon the Name of the Lord moſt high. But who can ſhew forth all his Praiſes, who can reckon up the Mercies of
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:153725:93"/> one Water-ſeaſon, Our ſafe Arrival under his Protection from our Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitations, needful Conveniences in this place for Soul and for Body, for daily Worſhip and for daily Bread. O Lord we bleſs thee that we have ſo many Mercies to bleſs thee for, that we have an Houſe, a Chappel built to bleſs thee in. O let us not want Hearts to bleſs thee with, for Chriſt his ſake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="thanksgiving">
               <head>VI.</head>
               <p>O Lord our God, whoſe Power, Wiſdom and Goodneſs are ſignally manifeſted in making the Fountains of Waters: We praiſe thee for theſe and all other Manifeſtations of thy Almighty Power, unſearchable Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and inexhauſtible Goodneſs. And we beſeech thee help us to walk before thee, as become thoſe who do indeed believe Thee to be ſuch, by fearing thee for thy Power, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the conduct of thy Wiſdom, and loving thee for thy Goodneſs, and
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:153725:94"/> all the Manifeſtations of it, both by thy Providence and Grace. Grant this, O moſt merciful Father, for the ſake of thy deareſt Son, and our dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Lord and Saviour, to whom with thy ſelf and thy moſt bleſſed Spirit be aſcribed everlaſting Honour, Praiſe and Glory. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="thanksgiving">
               <head>VII.</head>
               <p>Almighty Lord God, who by thy Power and Wiſdom haſt made the Fountains of the great Deep, and out of the depth of thy Mercy, that Fountain of Baptiſm, the Waters of which thou haſt conſecrated to the myſtical waſhing away of Sin; We moſt heartily bleſs thee for creating us after thy Image, for our being born in the boſom of thy Church, of Chriſtian Parents, in whoſe right and by whoſe care we were dedicated to thee in holy Baptiſm, and after brought up in the true Religion. We beſeech thee baptize us by the Holy Ghoſt: Waſh us from the guilt
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:153725:94"/> and filth of all our Sins: Juſtify us freely: Sanctify us throughly: Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate in us, O Lord, a clean Heart, and renew in us a right Spirit. In our Baptiſmal Waters inable us to quench all the fiery Darts of the Devil, and to waſh off all the Defilements of our ſinful Fleſh, and to diſſolve all the Snares of the Pomps and Vanities of this wicked World; all which we have ſolemnly renounced. And let the ſame Waters ſo moiſten our Hearts, that they may be fruitful in Faith, Repentance and new Obedience, that we may walk before thee in Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and true Holineſs all our days. To the Glory of God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther who created us, and God the Son who redeem'd us, and God the Holy Ghoſt, who, we hope, hath ſanctified us, to whoſe Name we were conſecrated, and to promote whoſe Glory is not leſs our Intereſt than it is our Duty, to which undivided Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and eternal Unity be everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Praiſe and Adoration. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="meditations">
            <pb facs="tcp:153725:95"/>
            <pb n="159" facs="tcp:153725:95"/>
            <head>Short Meditations and Ejaculations to be uſed whilſt the Waters are drinking.</head>
            <p>HOW early do we riſe to drink theſe Waters? In the Morning ſhall my Prayer prevent thee, O thou whoſe Compaſſions are new every morning.</p>
            <p>No Man can tell the Date of theſe Fountains, nor can any Man foretell their Period: Yet are they but as yeſterday to Him, <hi>who is yeſterday, to day, and the ſame for ever: Who was, who is, and is to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How many Glaſſes have been drunk from theſe Wells? how much more Water hath run waſte? how many yet remain in their pregnant
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:153725:96"/> Womb? and how many Millions of Drops would theſe amount to? yet all thoſe Drops, with all the Sands of theſe ſandy Deſarts, would not equal the Years of that Eternity, to which O my Soul, thou haſteneſt ſo faſt.</p>
            <p>Theſe rich Wells are in a low Valley, ſurrounded with high, ſandy, dry and barren Hills: The meek and lowly God will inrich with his Grace. <hi>He reſiſts the Proud, and gives Grace to the Humble.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The method of our Water-drinking is inſtructive: We begin with fewer Glaſſes, and riſe gradually till we ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive at a due Proportion: this we ſhould imitate.</p>
            <p>We muſt grow in Grace, go from Strength to Strength. <hi>The way of the Juſt is as the Morning-Light, which ſhineth more and more unto the perfect Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Chriſtian ſhould know no Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od, but Perfection. He that thinks
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:153725:96"/> he hath Grace enough, may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by be convinced he hath too little.</p>
            <p>When we are going off, we then decreaſe our Number, this we muſt avoid; 'tis bad to ſtand at a ſtay; for not to go forward is to go back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in the things of God. But to decline, ſadly forebodes our final go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing off.</p>
            <p>That Queſtion of our Lord, <hi>Where are the nine?</hi> was a cutting and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braiding one. Ten were healed, and but one among them was found thankful. How mean and deſpica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſoever I am, Lord, make me truly humble and thankful. 'Tis better to be a grateful <hi>Samaritan,</hi> than a grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs <hi>Iſraelite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lord, bleſs theſe Waters to us.</p>
            <p>Lord give us leave to uſe them. And Lord, give us both Cauſe and Hearts to be thankful for them.</p>
            <pb n="162" facs="tcp:153725:97"/>
            <p>O thou maker of the Fountains, make theſe uſeful to us all who drink of them.</p>
            <p>Lord give us to drink plenteouſly of the Wells of Salvation.</p>
            <p>O Lord who giveſt theſe Waters without our asking, We humbly ask thy Bleſſing upon the uſe of them.</p>
            <p>O thou Fountain of Living Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, evermore give us of thoſe Streams which flow from thee.</p>
            <p>Give us this day our daily Bread; whatever is needful for Health or Strength, whether Food or Phyſick.</p>
            <p>Impregnate theſe Waters, O Lord, with thine own Goodneſs.</p>
            <p>Lord let us have the uſe of theſe Waters by thy Leave; and a Bleſſing upon them by thy Love.</p>
            <pb n="163" facs="tcp:153725:97"/>
            <p>Lord ſuffer us not to provoke thee to Anger, where we come to ſeek Relief from thee.</p>
            <p>O Lamb of God, from under whoſe Throne flow Living Waters, waſh away our Sins by thoſe Waters.</p>
            <p>O thou Son of God, who waſt with thy Father when as yet there were no created Fountains abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Water, Manifeſt that Love to me which flows from the eternal Fountain of free Grace, and that Love wherewith thou lovedſt thine before the World was.</p>
            <p>Lord remove that Curſe our Sins have deſerved theſe Waters ſhould be imbittered by, and ſweeten them with Bleſſings we neither have nor can deſerve from thee.</p>
            <p>Good Lord help us to improve for thee all the Mercies we here or elſewhere receive, or hope for from thee.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="praises">
            <pb n="164" facs="tcp:153725:98"/>
            <head>Ejaculatory Praiſes.</head>
            <p>BLeſſed be the Maker of theſe Fountains, for all that Power, Wiſdom, Goodneſs manifeſted in the making of them. Bleſſed be God for any Bleſſing, now or formerly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by them.</p>
            <p>O thou Fountain of Goodneſs, who art Good, and doſt Good, we praiſe thee for all the Good thou ever didſt for any by theſe Good Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains.</p>
            <p>O that we could praiſe thee as thankfully, as thou giveſt theſe Waters freely.</p>
            <p>Bleſs the Lord, O my Soul, and all that is within me bleſs his holy Name. Bleſs the Lord, O my Soul, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:153725:98"/> not all his Benefits; who forgiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all thy Sins, and healeth all thy Diſeaſes.</p>
            <p>O all ye Works of the Lord, bleſs ye the Lord, praiſe him, and magnify him for ever.</p>
            <p>O ye <hi>Tunbridg-Wells,</hi> bleſs ye the Lord, praiſe him, and magnify him for ever.</p>
            <p>O let all who ever received Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit by the Waters of theſe Wells, bleſs the Lord, praiſe him, and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify him for ever.</p>
            <p>O my Soul, bleſs thou the Lord, praiſe him, and magnify him for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
            <p>Bleſſed be God for all the natural and ſupernatural Fountains he hath made, as the God of Nature, as the God of Grace.</p>
            <pb n="166" facs="tcp:153725:99"/>
            <p>Bleſſed be God for making us, and bleſſed be God for making all things for us: bleſſed be God for Springs of Common Water, and of Mineral Waters, for the Fountain of free Grace, and for the Covenant of Grace, for his Son and for his Spirit, for his Word and for his Sacraments, for all the means of Grace, and hopes of Glory. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:153725:99"/>
            <head>Books lately printed for <hi>Nathaniel Ranew</hi> at the King's-Arms in St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Church-Yard.</head>
            <p>THE Works of <hi>Joſephus,</hi> with great Diligence reviſed and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended according to the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent <hi>French</hi> Tranſlation of Monſieur <hi>D'ANDILLY.</hi> Alſo the Embaſſy of <hi>Philo Judaeus</hi> to the Emperor <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligula,</hi> with the References of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, a Map of the Holy Land, and divers other Copper Plates.</p>
            <p>The Principles of Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, with a large Body of Divinity methodically and familiarly handled by way of Queſtion and Anſwer, for the uſe of Families; together with <hi>Immanuel,</hi> or the myſtery of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation of the Son of God: By the moſt Reverend <hi>James <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> late
<pb facs="tcp:153725:100"/> Arch-biſhop of <hi>Armagh;</hi> to which is now added in this ſeventh Edition, twenty Sermons preach'd at <hi>Oxford</hi> before the King, and elſewhere, with the Life of the Author, and an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phabetical Table never before extant.</p>
            <p>Redemption of Time, the Duty and Wiſdom of Chriſtians in evil Days: Or, A Practical Diſcourſe, ſhewing what ſpecial Opportunities ought to be redeemed, what Miſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Time are to be avoided, with convincing Reaſons, quickening Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, and proper Directions for the right Improvement of precious Time. By <hi>John Wade</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Hammer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmith.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:153725:100"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153725:101"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153725:101"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153725:102"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153725:102"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153725:103"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153725:103" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
